[SOUND].
In this lecture, we're going to talk about
how to instantiate a vector space model,
so that we can get a very
specific ranking function.
So this is the, to continue
the discussion of the vector space model.
Which is one particular approach
to design ranking function.
And we are going to talk about how
we use the general framework of
the the vector space model.
As a guidance to instantiate the framework
to derive a specific ranking function.
And we're going to cover the simplest
instantiation of the framework.
So as we discussed in
the previous lecture.
The vector space model
is really a framework.
It isn't, didn't say.
As we discussed in the previous lecture,
vector space model is really a framework.
It doesn't, say many things.
So for
example here it shows that it did not say
how we should define the dimension.
It also did not say how we place
a documented vector in this space.
It did not say how we place a query
vector in this vector space.
And finally, it did not say how
we should match a similarity
between the query vector and
the document vector.
So, you can imagine,
in order to implement this model.
We have to see specifically,
how we are computing these vectors.
What is exactly xi and what is exactly yi?
This will determine where we
place the document vector.
Where we place a query vector.
And of course, we also need to say exactly
what will be the similarity function.
So if we can provide a definition
of the concepts that would
define the dimensions and
these xi's, or yi's.
And then, the waits of terms for
query and document.
Then we will be able to
place document vectors and
query vector in this well defined space.
And then,
if we also specify similarity function,
then we'll have well
defined ranking function.
So let's see how we can do that.
And think about
the the simpliciter instantiation.
Actually, I would suggest you to
pause the lecture at this point
spend a couple of minute to think about.
Suppose you are asked
to implement this idea.
You've come up with the idea
of vector space model.
But you still haven't figured out
how to compute this vector exactly,
how to define this similarity function.
What would you do?
So think for a couple of minutes and
then, proceed.
So let's think about some simplest ways
of instantiating this vector space model.
First, how do we define a dimension.
Well the obvious choice is we use
each word in our vocabulary
to define a dimension.
And a whole issue that there
are n words in our vocabulary,
therefore there are n dimensions.
Each word defines one dimension.
And this is basically the Bag
of Words Instantiation.
Now let's look at how we
place vectors in this space.
Again here, the simplest of strategy is to
use a bit vector to represent
both a query and a document.
And that means each element xi and
yi would be taking a value
of either zero or one.
When it's one,
it means the corresponding word is
present in the document or in the query.
When it's zero,
it's going to mean that it's absent.
So you can imagine if the user
types in a few word in your query.
Then the query vector,
we only have a few ones, many, many zeros.
The document vector in general
we have more ones of course,
but we also have many zeros.
So it seems the vocabulary
is generally very large.
Many words don't really
occur in a document.
Many words will only occasionally
occur in the document.
A lot of words will be absent
in a particular document.
So, now we have placed the documents and
the query in the vector space.
Let's look at how we
match up the similarity.
So, a commonly used similarity
measure here is Dot Product.
The dot product of two
vectors is simply defined as
the sum of the products of the
corresponding elements of the two vectors.
So here we see that it's
the product of x1 and the y1.
So here.
And then, x2 multiplied by y2.
And then finally xn multiplied by yn.
And then we take a sum here.
So that's the dot product.
Now we can represent this in a more
general way, using a sum here.
So this only one of the many different
ways of matching the similarity.
So now we see that we have defined the,
the dimensions.
We have defined the, the vectors.
And we have also defined
the similarity function.
So now we finally have
the Simplest Vector Space Model.
Which is based on the bit vector
representation, dot product similarity,
and bag of words instantiation.
And the formula looks like this.
So this is our formula.
And that's actually a particular retrieval
function, a ranking function all right?
Now, we can finally implement this
function using a program language and
then rank documents for query.
Now at this point you should
again pause the lecture
to think about how we can
interpret this score.
So we have gone through the process
of modeling the retrieval problem
using a vector space model.
And then, we make assumptions.
About how we place vectors in the vector
space and how we define the similarity.
So in the end we've got a specific
retrieval function shown here.
Now the next step is to think about
what of this individual function
actually makes sense?
I, can we expect this function
to actually perform well?
Where we use it to ramp it up,
for use in query.
So, it's worth thinking about, what is
this value that we are calculating?
So in the end, we've got a number,
but what does this number mean?
Is it meaningful?
So spend a couple minutes
to think about that.
And of course,
the general question here is do you
believe this is a good ranking function?
Would it actually work well?
So again,
think about how to interpret this value.
Is it actually meaningful?
Does it mean something?
So related to how well that
document matches the query.
So in order to assess
whether this simplest
vector space model actually works well,
let's look at the example.
So here I show some sample documents and
a simple query.
The query is news about
the presidential campaign.
And we have five documents here.
They cover different, terms in the query.
And if you look at the,
these documents for a moment.
You may realize that
some documents are probably relevant
in some cases or probably not relevant.
Now if I ask you to rank these documents,
how would you rank them?
This is basically our ideal ranking.
Right.
When humans can examine the documents and
then try to rank them.
Now, so think for a moment and
take a look at this slide.
And perhaps by pausing the lecture.
So I think most of you
would agree that d4,
and d3, are probably better than others.
Because they really cover the query well.
They match news,
presidential, and campaign.
So, it looks like that these two documents
are probably better than the others.
They should be ranked on top.
And the other three, d1, d2, and
d5, are really non-relavant.
So we can also say d4 and
d3 are relevent documents, and d1, d2, and
d5 are non-relevant.
So, now lets see if our vector
space model could do the same or
could do something closer.
So let's first think about how we actually
use this model to score documents.
Right here I show two documents, d1 and
d3, and we have the query also here.
In the vector space model, of course we
want to first compute the vectors for
these documents and the query.
Now I issue with the vocabulary
here as well, so
these are the n dimensions
that we'll be thinking about.
So what do you think is the vector
representation for the query?
Note that we are assuming
that we only use zero and one
to indicate whether a term is absent or
present in the query or in the document.
So these are zero, one bit vectors.
So what do you think is the query vector?
Well the query has four words here.
So for these four words, there would be a
one and for the rest, there will be zeros.
Now what about the documents?
It's the same.
So d1 has two rows, news and about.
So there are two ones here and
the rest are zeros.
Similarly, so
now that we have the two vectors,
let's compute the similarity.
And we're going to use dot product.
So you can see when we use dot product we
just, multiply the corresponding elements.
Right.
So
these two would be, form a,
be forming a product.
And these two will
generate another product.
And these two would generate yet
another product.
And so on and so forth.
Now you can,
you need to see if we do that.
We actually don't have to
care about these zeroes
because if whenever we have a zero,
the product will be zero.
So, when we take a sum
over all these pairs,
then the zero entries will be gone.
As long as you have one zero,
then the product would be zero.
So in the fact, we're just counting
how many pairs of one and one, right?
In this case, we have seen two.
So the result will be two.
So, what does that mean?
Well that means, this number or
the value of this scoring function.
Is simply the count of how many unique
query terms are matched in the document.
Because if a document,
if a term is matched in the document,
then there will be two ones.
If it's not, then there will
be zero on the document side.
Similarly, if the document has a term,.
But the terms not in the query there
will be zero in the query vector.
So those don't count.
So as a result this
scoring function basically
meshes how many unique query
terms are matched in a document.
This is how we interpret this score.
Now we can also take a look at the d3.
In this case,
you can see the result is three.
Because d3 matched the three distinctive
query words, news, presidential, campaign.
Whereas d1 only matched two.
Now in this case, it seems
reasonable to rank d3 on top of d1.
And this simplest vector
space model indeed does that.
So that looks pretty good.
However, if we examine this model in
detail, we likely will find some problems.
So here I'm going to show all
the scores for these five documents.
And you can even verify they are correct.
Because we're basically counting
the number of unique query
terms matched in each document.
Now note that this method
actually makes sense.
Right?
It basically means if a document matches
more unique query terms, then the document
will be assuming to be more relevant.
And that seems to make sense.
The only problem is here, we can note set
there are three documents, d2, d3, and d4.
And they tied with a three, as a score.
So that's a problem, because if you
look at them carefully it seems that
d4 should be right above d3.
Because d3 only mentioned
the presidential once.
But d4 mentioned it much more times.
In case of d3,
presidential could be extended mentioned.
But d4 is clearly above
presidential campaign.
Another problem is that d2 and
d3 also have the same soul.
But, if you look at the,
the three words that are matched.
In the case of d2, it matched the news,
about, and the campaign.
But in the case of d3, it match the news,
presidential, and campaign.
So intuitively, d3 is better.
Because matching presidential is more
important though than matching about.
Even though about and
the presidential are both in the query.
So intuitively,
we would like d3 to be ranked above d2.
But this model, doesn't do that.
So that means this is still not good
enough, we have to solve these problems.
To summarize,
in this lecture we talked about how
to instantiate a vector space model.
We may need to do three things.
One is to define the dimension.
The second is to
decide how to place documents
as vectors in the vector space.
And to also place a query in
the vector space as a vector.
And third is to define
the similarity between two vectors,
particularly the query vector and
the document vector.
We also talked about a very simple way
to instantiate the vector space model.
Indeed, that's probably the simplest
vector space model that we can derive.
In this case,
we use each word to define a dimension.
We use a zero one bit vector to
represent a document or a query.
In this case, we basically only care
about word presence or absence.
We ignore the frequency.
And we use the dot product
as the similarity function.
And with such a, a, in situation.
And we showed that the scoring
function is basically to score
a document based on the number of distinct
query words matched in the document.
We also show that such a single vector
space model still doesn't work well,
and we need to improve it.
And this is the topic that we're
going to cover in the next lecture.
[MUSIC]