This lecture is about document length
normalization in the vector space model.
In this lecture we are going to continue
the discussion of the vector space model
in particular we are going to discuss.
The issue of document
length normalization.
So far in the lectures about
the vector space model,
we have used the various
signals from the document to
assess the matching of the document
though with a preorder.
In particular we have
considered the term frequency,
the count of a term in a document.
We have also considered a,
it's global statistics such as
IDF in words document frequency.
But we have not considered
a document length.
So, here I show two example documents.
D4 is much shorter with only 100 words.
D6 on the other hand has 5,000 words.
If you look at the matching of these
query words we see that in D6 there
are more matchings of the query words but
one might reason that D6 may
have matched these query words.
In a scattered manner.
So maybe the topic of d6 is not
really about the topic of the query.
So the discussion of a campaign
at the beginning of the document
may have nothing to do with the mention
of presidential at the end.
In general,
if you think about the long documents,
they would have a higher
chance to match any query.
In fact, if you generate a,
a long document that randomly sampling,
sampling words from
the distribution of words,
then eventually you probably
will match any query.
So in this sense we should
penalize no documents because they
just naturally have better
chances to match any query.
And this is our idea of document answer.
We also need to be careful in avoiding
to overpenalize small documents.
On the one hand,
we want to penalize a long document.
But on the other hand,
we also don't want to over-penalize them.
And the reason is because a document that
may be long because of different reason.
In one case the document may be more
long because it uses more words.
So for example think about
the article of a research paper.
It would use more words than
the corresponding abstract.
So this is the case where we probably
should penalize the matching of
a long document such as, full paper.
When we compare the matching
of words in such
long document with matching of
the words in the short abstract.
Then long papers generally have a higher
chance of matching query words.
Therefore we should penalize them.
However, there is another case
when the document is long and
that is when the document
simply has more content.
Now consider another
case of a long document,
where we simply concatenated a lot
of abstracts of different papers.
In such a case, obviously, we don't
want to penalize such a long document.
Indeed, we probably don't want to penalize
such a document because it's long.
So that's why we need to be careful.
About using the right
degree of penalization.
A method that has been working well
based on recent research is called,
pivot length normalization.
And in this case the idea is to use.
The average document length as a P word,
as a reference point.
That means we will assume that for
the average length documents,
the score is about right.
So, the normalizer would be 1.
But if a document is longer than
the average document length
then there will be some penalization.
Where as if it's shorter than
there's even some reward.
So this is an illustrator
that using this slide.
On the axis,
s axis you can see the length of document.
On the y-axis we show the normalizer,
in the case pivoted length normalization
formula for the normalizer is
is seem to be interpolation of one and
the normalize the document lengths,
controlled by a parameter b here.
So, you can see here,
when we first divide the lengths of the
document by the average document length.
This not only gives us
some sense about the,
how this document is compared with
the average document length, but
also gives us a benefit of not
worrying about the unit of
length, we can measure the length
by words or by characters.
Anyway this normalizer has
an interesting property.
First we see that if we set the parameter
b to 0 then the value would be 1,
so there's no pair,
length normalization at all.
So b in this sense controls the length
normalization, where as if we set
d to a non-zero value, then
the normalizer will look like this, right.
So the value would be higher for
documents that are longer than
the average document length.
Where as the value of the normalizer
will be short- will be smaller for
shorter documents.
So in this sense we see there's
a penalization for long documents.
And there's a reward for short documents.
The degree of penalization
is conjured by b.
Because if we set b to a larger
value then the normalizer.
What looked like this.
There's even more penalization for
long documents and more reward for
the short documents.
By adjusting b which
varies from zero to one
we can control the degree
of length normalization.
So if we're plucking this length
normalization factor into
the vector space model ranking functions
that we have already examined.
Then we will end up heading with formulas,
and
these are in fact the state of
the are vector space models.
Formulas.
So, let's talk an that,
let's take a look at the each of them.
The first one's called a pivoted length
normalization vector space model.
And, a reference in the end has detail
about the derivation of this model.
And, here, we see that it's basically
the TFIDF weighting model that we have
discussed.
The IDF component should be
very familiar now to you.
There is also a query term
frequency component, here.
And, and then in the middle there is.
And normalize the TF.
And in this case,
we see we use the double algorithm,
as we discussed before, and this is to
achieve a sublinear transformation.
But we also put document length
normalizer in the bottom, all right so
this would cause penalty for
a long document, because the larger
the denominator is, the denominator is
then the smaller the shift weight is.
And this is of course controlled
by the parameter b here.
And you can see again, b is set to 0, and
there, there is no length normalization.
Okay.
So this is one of the two most effective.
Not this base model of formulas.
The next one called a BM25,
or Okapi, is, also similar.
In that, it also has a i, df component
here, and a query df component here.
But in the middle, the normalization's
a little bit different.
As we expand there is this or
copied here for transformation here.
And that does, sublinear
transformation with an upper bound.
In this case we have put the length
normalization factor here.
We are adjusting k, but
it achieves a similar factor
because we put a normalizer
in the denominator.
Therefore again, if a document is longer,
then the term weight will be smaller.
So, you can see, after we have gone
through all the instances that we talked
about, and we have,
in the end, reached the,
basically the state of
the art mutual function.
So, so far we have talked
about mainly how to place
the document matter in the matter space.
And this has played an important role
in uh,determining the factors of
the function.
But there are also other dimensions
where we did not really examine detail.
For example can we further
improve the instantiation of
the dimension of the vector space model.
Now we've just assumed
that the back of words.
So each dimension is a word.
But obviously we can see
there are many other choices.
For example, stemmed words, those
are the words that have been transformed
into the same rule form.
So that computation and computing will all
become the same and they can be matched.
We need to stop water removal.
This is removes on very common
words that don't carry any content.
Like the or of,
we use the phrases to define that [SOUND].
We can even use late in the semantica,
an answer sort of find in the sum cluster.
So words that represent
a legend of concept as one.
We can also use smaller units,
like a character in grams.
Those are sequences of n characters for
dimensions.
However, in practice people have found
that the bag-of-words representation
with the phrases is where
the the most effective one.
And it's also efficient so
this is still so
far the most popular dimension
instantiation method and
it's used in all the major search engines.
I should also mention that sometimes
we did to do language specific and
domain specific organization.
And this is actually very important as
we might have variations of the terms.
That might prevent us from
matching them with each other.
Even though they mean the same thing.
And some of them, which is like Chinese,
the results of the.
Segmenting text to obtain word boundaries.
Because it's just
a sequence of characters.
A word might, might correspond to
one character or two characters or
even three characters.
So it's easier in English when we
have a space to separate the words.
But in some other languages we may need
to do some natural language processing
to figure out the,
where are the boundaries for words.
There is also possibility to
improve this in narrative function.
And so
far we have used the about product, but
one can imagine there are other matches.
For example we can match the cosine
of the angle between two vectors, or
we can use Euclidean distance measure.
And these are all possible.
The dot product seems still the best and
one of the reasons is
because it's very general.
In fact, it's sufficiently general.
If you consider the possibilities of
doing weighting in different ways.
So, for example,
cosine measure can be regarded as the dot
product of two normalized vectors.
That means we first normalize each vector,
and then we take the dot product.
That would be equivalent
to the cosine measure.
I just mentioned that the BM25.
Seems to be one of the most
effective formulas.
But there has been also further
development in, improving BM25, although
none of these works have
changed the BM25 fundamentally.
So in one line of work,
people have derived BM25 F.
Here F stands for field, and
this is a little use BM25 for
documents with a structures.
For example you might consider
title field, the abstract, or
body of the reasearch article, or
even anchor text on the web pages.
Those are the text fields that
describe links to other pages.
And these can all be
combined with a appropriate
weight on different fields to help
improve scoring for document.
Use BM25 for such a document.
And the obvious choice is to
apply BM25 for each field, and
then combine the scores.
Basically, the ideal of BM25F,
is to first combine
the frequency counts of tons in all
the fields and then apply BM25.
Now this has advantage of avoiding over
counting the first occurrence of the term.
Remember in the sublinear
transformation of TF,
the first recurrence is very important
then, and contributes a large weight.
And if we do that for all the fields, then
the same term might have gained a, a lot
of advantage in every field, but when we
combine these word frequencies together.
We just do the transformation one time,
and
that time then the extra occurrences will
not be counted as fresh first occurrences.
And this method has been working very
well for scoring structured documents.
The other line of extension is called
a BM25 plus and this line, arresters
have addressed the problem of over
penalization of long documents by BM25.
So to address this problem,
the fix is actually quite simple.
We can simply add a small constant
to the TF normalization formula.
But what's interesting is that we can
analytically prove that by doing such
a small modification,
we will fix the problem of a,
over penalization of long
documents by the original BM25.
So the new formula called
BM25-plus is empirically and
analytically shown to be better than BM25.
So to summarize all what we have
said about the Vector Space Model.
Here are the major takeaway points.
First, in such a model,
we use the similarity notion of relevance,
assuming that the relevance of
a document with respect to a query is
basically proportional to the similarity
between the query and the document.
So, naturally,
that implies that the query and
document must be represented in
the same way, and in this case,
we represent them as vectors in
high dimensional vector space.
Where the dimensions are defined by
words or concepts or terms in general.
And we generally need to use a lot of
heuristics to design a ranking function.
We use some examples which show
the need for several heuristics,
including TF waiting and transformation.
And IDF weighting, and
document length normalization.
These major heuristics are the most
important heuristics to ensure such
a general ranking function to
work well for all kinds of tasks.
And finally BM25 and
Pivoted normalization seem
to be the most effective
formulas out of that Space Model.
Now I have to say that, I've put BM25
in the category of Vector Space Model.
But in fact the BM25 has
been derived using model.
So the reason why I've put it in
the vector space model is first
the ranking function actually has a nice
interpretation in the vector space model.
We can easily see it looks very
much like a vector space model
with a special weighting function.
The second reason is because the original
BM25 has a somewhat different from of IDF.
And that form of IDF actually
doesn't really work so
well as the standard IDF
that you have seen here.
So as a effective original function
BM25 should probably use a heuristic
modification of the IDF to make that
even more like a vector space model.
There are some additional readings.
The first is a paper about
the pivoted length normalization.
It's an excellent example of using
empirical data enhances to suggest a need
for length normalization, and then further
derived a length normalization formula.
The second is the original
paper when the was proposed.
The third paper has
a thorough discussion of and
its extensions, particularly BM-25F.
And finally, the last paper
has a discussion of improving
BM-25 to correct the overpenalization
of long documents.
[MUSIC]