[SOUND].
In this lecture, we're going to talk about
how to improve the instant changing of
the Vector Space Model.
This is the continued discussion
of the Vector Space Model.
We're going to focus on how to improve
the instant changing of this model.
In a previous lecture,
you have seen that with simple
situations of the Vector Space Model,
we can come up with
a simple scoring function that
would give us, basically,
a count of how many unique query
terms are matching the document.
We also have seen that this function
has a problem as shown on this slide.
In particular,
if you look at these three documents,
they will all get the same score because
they match the three unique query words.
But intuitively we would like,
d4 to be ranked above d3.
And d2 is really non relevant.
So the problem here is that
this function couldn't capture
the following characteristics.
First, we would like to
give more gratitude to d4
because it matches the presidential
more times than d3.
Second, intuitively matching
presidential should be more important
than matching about, because about is
a very common word that occurs everywhere.
It doesn't really carry that much content.
So, in this lecture,
let's see how we can improve the model
to solve these two problems.
It's worth thinking at this point about
why do we have these four problems.
If we look back at
the assumptions we have made
while substantiating the Vector
Space Model, we will realize that
the problem is really coming
from some of the assumptions.
In particular, it has to do with how we
place the vectors in the vector space.
So then, naturally,
in order to fix these problems,
we have to revisit those assumptions.
Perhaps, you will have
to use different ways to
instantiate the Vector Space Model.
In particular, we have to place
the vectors in a different way.
So, let's see how can we prove this?
Well, our natural thought is in order
to consider multiple times of a term
in a document.
We should consider the term frequency
instead of just the absence or presence.
In order to consider the difference
between a document where a query
term occurred multiple times and the one
where the query term occurred just once.
We have to concede a term frequency,
the count of a term being in the document.
In the simplest model, we only model
the presence and absence of a term.
We ignore the actual number of times
that a term occurs in a document.
So let's add this back.
So we're going to do then represent
a document by a vector with
term frequency as element.
So, that is to say, now,
the elements of both the query vector and
the document vector will not be zero once,
but
instead there will be the counts of
a word in the query or the document.
So this would bring additional
information about the document.
So this can be seen as a more accurate
representation of our documents.
So, now let's see what the formula
would look like if we change
this representation.
So as you see on this slide,
we still use that product, and,
so the formula looks
very similar in the form.
In fact, it looks identical, but
inside of the sum of cos xi and
yi are now different.
They're now the counts of words
i in the query and the document.
Now at this point, I also suggest you
to pause the lecture for moment and
just we'll think about how we have
interpret the score of this new function.
It's doing something very similar
to what the simplest VSM is doing.
But because of the change of the vector,
now the new score has
a different interpretation.
Can you see the difference?
And it has to do with
the consideration of multiple
occurrences of the same
time in the document.
More importantly, we''ll try to know
whether this would fix the problem of
the simplest vector space model.
So, let's look at the this example again.
So suppose, we change the vector
to term frequency vectors.
Now, let's look at these
three documents again.
The query vector is the same because
all these words occurred exactly once
in the query.
So the vector is still 0 1 vector.
And in fact,
d2 is also essential in representing
the same way because none of these
words has been repeated many times.
As a result, the score is also the same,
still three.
The same issue for d3 and
we still have a 3.
But d4 would be different, because now,
presidential occurred twice here.
So the end in the four presidential in
the [INAUDIBLE] would be 2 instead of 1.
As a result, now the score for
d4 is higher.
It's a four now.
So this means, by using term frequency,
we can now rank d4 above d2 and
d3 as we hope to.
So this solve the problem with default.
But, we can also see that d2 and
d3 are still featured in the same way.
They still have identical scores,
so it did not fix the problem here.
So, how can we fix this problem?
We would like, to give more credit for
matching presidential than matching about.
But how can we solve
the problem in a general way?
Is there any way to determine which word
should be treated more importantly and
which word can be, basically ignored.
About is such a word.
And which it does not really
carry that much content,
we can essentially ignore that.
We sometimes call such a word,
a stock word.
Those are generally very frequent and
they occur everywhere,
matching it, doesn't really mean anything.
But computation how can we capture that?
So again, I encourage you to
think a little bit about this.
Can you come up with any
statistical approaches to somehow
distinguish presidential from about.
If you think about it for
a moment, you realize that,
one difference is that a word
like above occurs everywhere.
So if you count the currents of the water
in the whole collection that we
would see that about as much higher for
this than presidential, which it tends
to occur only in some documents.
So this idea suggests
that we could somehow
use the global statistics of terms or
some other formation to try to
down weight the element for
about in the vector representation of d2.
At the same time,
we hope to somehow increase the weight
of presidential in the vector of d3.
If we can do that, then,
we can expect that d2 will get
the overall score to be less than three,
while d3 will get the score about three.
Then, we'll be able to
rank d3 on top of d2.
So how can we do this systematically?
Again, we can rely on some
steps that people count.
And in this case, the particular idea is
called the Inverse Document Frequency.
We have seen document frequency.
As one signal used in,
the moding retrieval functions.
We discussed this in a previous lecture.
So here's the specific way of using it.
Document frequency is the count of
documents that contain a particular term.
Here, we say inverse document frequency
because we actually want to reword a word
that doesn't occur in many documents.
And so, the way to incorporate this
into our vector [INAUDIBLE] is
then to modify the frequency
count by multiplying
it by the idea of the corresponding
word as shown here.
If we didn't do that,
then we can penalize common
words which generally have a low idea of,
and
reward real words,
which we're have a higher IDF.
So most specific [INAUDIBLE] IDF
can be defined as the logarithm
of M plus one divided by k,
where M is the total number of
documents in the collection,k is df or
document frequency.
The total number of documents
containing the word W.
Now, if you plot this
function by varying k,
then you will see the curve
that look like this.
In general, you can see it
would give a higher value for
a low DF word, a rare word.
You can also see the maximum value
of this function is log of M plus 1.
Will be interesting for you to think about
what's minimum value for this function?
This could be interesting exercise.
Now, the specific function
may not be as important as
the heuristic to simply
penalize popular terms.
But it turns out this particular
function form has also worked very well.
Now, whether there is a better
form of function here,
is the open research question.
But, it's also clear that if we use
a linear kernalization like what's
shown here with this line, then, it may
not be as reasonable as the standard IDF.
In particular, you can see
the difference in the standard IDF,
and we,
somehow have a [INAUDIBLE] point here.
After this point, we're going to say these
terms are essentially not very useful.
They can be essentially ignored.
And this makes sense when the term
occurs so frequently, and
let's say a term occurs in more
than 50% of the documents.
Then the term is unlikely very important
and it's, it's basically, a common term.
It's not very important to match this
word, so with the standard IDF, you can
see it's, basically, assumed that they all
have lower weights, there's no difference.
But if you look at the linear
kernelization, at this point there is,
there's some difference.
So intuitively, we want to focus more
on the discrimination of low DF words,
rather than these common words.
Well, of course, which one works better,
still has to be validated
by using the empirically related data set.
And we have to use users to
judge which results of that.
So now let's see how this
can solve problem two.
So now,
let's look at the two documents again.
Now without IDF weighting, before,
we just have [INAUDIBLE] vectors,
but with IDF weighting we
now can adjust the DF weight
by multiplying the, with the IDF value.
For example here, you can see is
the adjustment in particular for
about, there is an adjustment
by using the IDF value of about
which is smaller than the IDF
value of presidential.
So if you look at these,
the IDF will distinguish these two words.
As a result, adjustment here would be
larger, would make this weight larger.
So if we score with these new vectors, and
what would happen is that the, of course,
they share the same weights for news and
the campaign, but the margin of about and
presidential with this grouping may.
So now as a result of IDF weighting,
we will have d3 to be ranked above d2.
Because it matched rail word,
where as d2 matched common word.
So this shows that the idea of
weighting can solve problem two.
So, how effective is this model in
general when we use TF-IDF weighting?
Well, let's look at all these
documents that we have seen before.
These are the new scores
of the new documents.
But how effective is this
new weighting method and
new scoring function, all right?
So now let's see overall how effective
is this new ranking function
with TF-IDF Weighting?
Here, we show all the five documents
that we have seen before, and
these are their scores.
Now, we can see the scores for
the first four
documents here seem to
be quite reasonable.
They are as we expected.
However, we also see a new problem.
Because now d5, here,
which did not have a very high
score with our simplest
vector space model.
Now, after it has a very high score.
In fact, it has the highest score here.
So, this creates a new problem.
This actually a common phenomenon
in designing material functions.
Basically, when you try
to fix one problem,
you tend to introduce other problems.
And that's why it's very tricky how
to design effective ranking function.
And what's what's the best ranking
function is the open research question.
Researchers are still working on that.
But in the next few lecture, we're
going to also talk about some additional
ideas to further improve this model and
try to fix this problem.
So to summarize this lecture,
we've talked about how to
improve this vector space model.
And we've got to improve the [INAUDIBLE]
of the vector space model based on
TF-IDF weighting.
So the improvement, most of it,
is on the placement of the vector.
Where we give higher weight to a term
that occurred many times in the document,
but infrequently in the whole collection.
And we have seen that this improved
model indeed works better than
the simplest vector space model, but
it also still has some problems.
In the next lecture,
we're going to look at the how to
address these additional problems.
[MUSIC]