[SOUND] This lecture is about
the text retrieval problem.
This picture shows our overall plan for
lectures.
In the last lecture, we talked about
the high level strategies for text access.
We talked about push versus pull.
Search engines are the main tools for
supporting the pull mode.
Starting from this lecture,
we're going to talk about the how
search engines work in detail.
So first,
it's about the text retrieval problem.
We're going to talk about
the three things in this lecture.
First, we'll define text retrieval.
Second, we're going to make
a comparison between text retrieval and
the related task, database retrieval.
Finally, we're going to talk about the
document selection versus document ranking
as two strategies for
responding to a user's query.
So what is text retrieval?
It should be a task that's familiar
to most of us because we're using web
search engines all the time.
So text retrieval is basically a task
where the system would respond
to a user's query with relevant lock-ins,
basically through
supported querying as one way to implement
the poor mold of information access.
So the scenario's the following.
You have a collection of text documents.
These documents could be all
the web pages on the web.
Or all the literature articles
in the digital library or
maybe all the text files in your computer.
A user will typically give a query to the
system to express the information need.
And then the system would return
relevant documents to users.
Relevant documents refer to those
documents that are useful to the user who
typed in the query.
Now this task is a often
called information retrieval.
But literally, information retrieval
would broadly include the retrieval of
other non-textual information as well.
For example, audio, video, et cetera.
It's worth noting that text
retrieval is at the core of
information retrieval in the sense
that other medias such as
video can be retrieved by
exploiting the companion text data.
So for example,
can the image search engines actually
match a user's query with
the companion text data of the image?
This problem is also called the,
the search problem,
and the technology is often called
search technology in industry.
If you ever take on course in databases,
it'll be useful to pause
the lecture at this point and
think about the differences between
text retrieval and database retrieval.
Now these two tasks
are similar in many ways.
But there are some important differences.
So, spend a moment to think about
the differences between the two.
Think about the data and information
managed by a search engine versus
those that are man,
managed by a database system.
Think about the difference between
the queries that you typically specify for
a database system versus the queries that
typed in by users on the search engine.
And then finally think about the answers.
What's the difference between the two?
Okay, so
if we think probably the information out
there are managed by the two systems.
We will see that in text retrieval,
the data is unstructured, it's free text.
But in databases, they are structured
data, where there is a clear defined
schema to tell you this column
is the names of people and
that column is ages, et cetera.
In unstructured text,
it's not obvious what are the names
of people mentioned in the text.
Because of this difference,
we can also see that text information
tends to be more ambiguous.
And we'll talk about that in the natural
language processing lecture.
Whereas in databases, the data tend
to have well-defined semantics.
There is also important
difference in the queries, and
this is partly due to the difference
in the information, or data.
So text queries tend to be ambiguous,
whereas in their research,
the queries are particularly well-defined.
Think about the SQL query,
that would clear the specify
what records to be returned.
So it has very well defined semantics.
Queue all queries or naturally ending
queries tend to be incomplete.
Also in that it doesn't really,
fully specify what documents
should be retrieved.
Whereas, in the database search,
the SQL query
can be regarded as a computer
specification for what should be returned.
And because of these differences,
the answers would be also different.
In the case of text retrieval,
we're looking for relevant documents.
In the database search,
we are retrieving records or
matched records with the SQL query,
more precisely.
Now in the case of text retrieval,
what should be the right answers to
a query is not very well specified,
as we just discussed.
So it's unclear what should be
the right answers to a query.
And this has very important consequences,
and
that is text retrieval is
an empirically defined problem.
And so this a problem because
if it's empirically defined,
then we cannot mathematically prove one
method is better than another method.
That also means we must rely
on emperical evaluation
more than users to know
which method works better.
And that's why we have one lecture,
actually more than one lectures
to cover the issue of evaluation.
Because this is a very important topic for
search engines.
Without knowing how to evaluate
an algorithm appropriately,
there's no way to tell whether we
have got the better algorithm or
whether one system is better than another.
So now let's look at
the problem in a formal way.
So this slide shows a formal formulation
of the text retrieval problem.
First, we have our vocabulary set which
is just a set of words in a language.
Now here,
we're considering just one language, but
in reality on the web there might
be multiple natural languages.
We have text that are in
all kinds of languages.
But here for simplicity, we just
assume there is one kind of language.
As the techniques used for
retrieving data from multiple languages,.
Are more or
less similar to the techniques used for
retrieving documents in one language.
Although there is important difference,
the principles and
methods are very similar.
Next we have the query,
which is a sequence of words.
And so here you can see the query
is defined as a sequence of words.
Each q sub i is a word in the vocabulary.
A document is defined in the same way.
So it's also a sequence of words.
And here,
d sub ij is also a word in the vocabulary.
Now typically, the documents
are much longer than queries.
But there are also cases where
the documents may be very short.
So you can think about the,
what might be a example of that case.
I hope you can think of,
of twitter search, all right?
Tweets are very short.
But in general,
documents are longer then the queries.
Now, then we have
a collection of documents.
And this collection can be very large.
So think about the web.
It could, could be very large.
And then the goal of text retrieval is
you'll find the set of relevant documents,
which we denote by R of q,
because it depends on the query.
And this is, in general, a subset of
all the documents in the collection.
Unfortunately, this set of random
documents is generally unknown,
and usually depend in the sense that for
the same query typed
in by different users, the expected
relevant documents may be different.
The query given to us by
the user is only a hint
on which document should be in this set.
And indeed, the user is generally unable
to specify what exactly should be in
the set, especially in the case of a web
search where the collection is so large.
The user doesn't have complete
knowledge about the whole collection.
So, the best a search system can do is
to compute an approximation of
this relevent document set.
So we denote it by R prime of q.
So, formally, we can see the task
is to compute this R prime of q,
an approximation of
the relevant documents.
So how can we do that?
Now, imagine if you are now asked
to write a program to do this.
What would you do?
Now think for a moment.
Right, so these are your input.
With the query, the documents and
then you will have computed
the answers to this query,
which is set of documents that
would be useful to the user.
So how would you solve the problem?
In general there are two
strategies that we can use.
All right, the first strategy
is to do document selection.
And that is, we're going to have
a binary classification function, or
binary classified.
That's a function that
will take a document and
query as input, and
then give a zero or one as output,
to indicate whether this document
is relevant to the query, or not.
So in this case, you can see the document.
The, the relevant document
set is defined as follows.
It basically, all the documents that
have a value of one by this function.
And so in this case,
you can see the system must have decided
if a document is relevant or not.
Basically, that has to say
whether it's one or zero.
And this is called absolute relevance.
Basically, it needs to know exactly
whether it's going to be useful
to the user.
Alternatively, there's another
strategy called document ranking.
Now in this case,
the system is not going to make a call
whether a document is relevant or not.
Rather, the system's going to
use a real value function, f,
here that would simply give us a value.
That would indicate which
document is more likely relevant.
So it's not going to make a call whether
this document is relevant or not,
but rather it would say which
document is more likely relevant.
So this function then can be
used to rank the documents.
And then we're going to let the user
decide where to stop when the user looks
at the documents.
So we have a threshold,
theta, here to determine
what documents should be
in this approximation set.
And we're going to assume that all
the documents that are ranked above this
threshold are in the set.
Because in effect, these are the documents
that we delivered to the user.
And theta is a cutoff
determined by the user.
So here we've got some collaboration from
the user in some sense because we
don't really make a cutoff, and
the user kind of helped
the system make a cutoff.
So in this case, the system only needs
to decide if one document is more likely
relevant than another.
And that is, it only needs for
determined relative relevance as
opposed to absolute relevance.
Now you can probably already
sense that relevant,
relative relevance would be easier
to determine the absolute relevance.
Because in the first case,
we have to say exactly whether
a document is relevant or not, right?
And it turns out that ranking is indeed
generally preferred to document selection.
So let's look this these two
strategies in more detail.
So this pictures shows how it works.
So on the left side,
we see these documents.
And we use the pluses to
indicate the relevant documents.
So we can see the true relevant
documents here consists
this set of true relevant documents
consists of these pluses, these documents.
And with the document selection function,
we can do,
basically classify them into two groups,
relevant documents and non-relevant ones.
Of course, the classifier will not be
perfect, so it will make mistakes.
So here we can see in the approximation of
the relevant documents we have
got some non-relevant documents.
And similarly, there's a relevant document
that that's misclassified as non-relevant.
In the case of document ranking,
we can see the system seems like
simply ranks all the documents in
the descending order of the scores.
And we're going to let the user stop
wherever the user wants to stop.
So if a user wants to examine more
documents, then the user will
go down the list to examine more and
stop at the lower position.
But if the user only wants to
read a few random documents,
the user might stop at the top position.
So in this case,
the user stops at d4, so the effect,
we have delivered these
four documents to our user.
So as I said,
ranking is generally preferred.
And one of the reasons is
because the classifier,
in the case of document selection,
is unlikely accurate.
Why?
Because the only clue is usually
the query.
But the query may not be accurate, in the
sense that it could be overly constrained.
For example, you might expect the relevant
documents to talk about all these
topics you, by using specific vocabulary,
and as a result,
you might match no random documents,
because in the collection,
no others have discussed the topic
using these vocabularies.
All right.
So in this case,
we'll see there is this problem of
no relevant documents to return in
the case of overly constrained query.
On the other hand, if the query is
under constrained, for example,
if the query does not have sufficient
discriminating words you'll
find in relevant documents,
you may actually end up having.
over delivery.
And this is when you thought these
words might be sufficient to
help you find the relevant documents, but
it turns out that they're not sufficient.
And there are many distraction
documents using similar words.
And so this is the case of over delivery.
Unfortunately, it's very hard to find the
right position between these two extremes.
Why?
Because, when the users looking for
the information in general,
the user does not have a good knowledge
about the the information to be found.
And in that case, the user does
not have a good knowledge about
what vocabularies will be used
in those random documents.
So it's very hard for
a user to pre-specify
the right level of of constraints.
Even if the class file is accurate,
we also still want to rank these
relevant documents because they
are generally not equally relevant.
Relevance is often a matter of degree.
So we must prioritize these documents for
user to exam.
And this, note that this
prioritization is very important,
because a user cannot digest
all the contents at once.
The user generally would have to
look at each document sequentially.
And therefore, it would make
sense to feed users with the most
relevant documents, and
that's what ranking is doing.
So for these reasons ranking
is generally preferred.
Now, this preference also has
a theoretical justification, and
this is given by the probability
ranking principle.
In the end of this lecture
there is a reference for this.
This principal says, returning a ranked
list of documents in descending order of
probability, that a document
is relevant to the query,
is the optimal strategy under
the following two assumptions.
First, the utility of a document to a user
Is independent of the utility
of any other document.
Second, a user would be assumed to
browse the results sequentially.
Now it's easy to understand why
these two assumptions are needed,
in order to justify for
the ranking, strategy.
Because, if the documents are independent,
then we can evaluate the utility
of each document that's separate.
And this would allow us to compute
a score for each document independently.
And then we're going to rank these
documents based on those scores.
The second assumption is to say that the
user would indeed follow the rank list.
If the user is not going to follow
the ranked list, is not going to examine
the documents sequentially, then obviously
the ordering would not be optimal.
So under these two assumptions, we can
theoretically justify the ranking strategy
is in fact the best that you could do.
Now I've put one question here.
Do these 2 assumptions hold?
Now I suggest you to pause the lecture for
a moment to think about these.
Now can you think of some
examples that would suggest
these assumptions aren't necessarily true?
Now if you think for
a moment you may realize none of
the assumptions is actually true.
For example in the case of
independence assumption, we might have
identical documents that have similar
content or exactly the same content.
If you look at each of them alone,
each is relevant.
But if the user has already seen
one of them, we assume it's
generally not very useful for the user
to see another similar or duplicate one.
So clearly the utility of
a document is dependent
on other documents that the user has seen.
In some other cases, you might see
a scenario where one document that may not
be useful to the user, but when three
particular documents are put together,
they provide answer to
the user's question.
So this is collective relevance.
And that also suggests that
the value of the document
might depend on other documents.
Sequential browsing generally would make
sense if you have a ranked list there.
But even if you have a run list,
there is evidence showing that
users don't always just go strictly
sequentially through the entire list.
They sometimes would look at
the bottom for example, or skip some.
And if you think about the more
complicated interfaces that would possibly
use like, two dimensional interface
where you can put additional information
on the screen, then sequential browsing
is a very restrictive assumption.
So the point here is that,
none of these assumptions is really true,
but nevertheless,
the probability ranking principle
establishes some solid foundation for
ranking as a primary task for
search engines.
And this has actually been the basis for
a lot of research work in
information retrieval.
And many algorithms have been
designed based on this assumption.
Despite that the assumptions
aren't necessarily true.
And we can, address this problem by
doing post processing of a ranked list.
For example, to remove redundancy.
So to summarize this lecture,
the main points that you can
take away are the following.
First, text retrieval is
an empirically defined problem.
And that means which algorithm is
better must be judged by the users.
Second, document ranking
is generally prefer and
this is, will help users prioritize
examination of search results.
And this is also to bypass the difficulty
in determining absolute relevance,
because we can get some help from users
in determining where to make the cut off.
It's more flexible.
So this further suggests that
the main technical challenge
in designing the search engine is with
designing effective ranking function.
In other words, we need to define
what is the value of this function f
on the query and document pair.
Now how to design such a function is
a main topic in the following lectures.
There are two suggested
additional readings.
The first is the classic paper on
probability ranking principle.
The second, is a must read for anyone
doing research information retrieval.
It's classical IR book,
which has excellent coverage of
the main research results in early days,
up to the time when the book was written.
Chapter six of this book has
an in depth discussion of
the probability of the ranking principal,
and
the probabilistic retrieval models,
in general.
[MUSIC]