[MUSIC]
This lecture is a overview
of text retrieval methods.
In the previous lecture we introduced
you to the problem of text retrieval.
We explained that the main problem is
to design a ranking function to rank
documents for a query.
In this lecture,
we will give a overview of different
ways of designing this ranking function.
So the problem is the following.
We have a query that has
a sequence of words, and
a document that, that's also a sequence of
words, and we hope to define the function
f that can compute a score based
on the query and document.
So the main challenge you here is with
designing a good ranking function that can
rank all the relevant documents,
on top of all the non-relevant ones.
Now clearly this means our
function must be able to measure
the likelihood that a document
d is relevant to a query q.
That also means we have to have
some way to define relevance.
In particular in order to implement
the program to do that we have to have
a computational definition of relevance,
and we achieve this goal by
designing a retrieval model, which
gives us a formalization of relevance.
Now, over many decades,
researchers have designed
many different kinds of retrieval models,
and they fall into different categories.
First, one fair many of the models
are based on the similarity idea.
Basically, we assume that if
a document is more similar to the query
than another document is,
then we would say the first document
is more relevant than the second one.
So in this case,
the ranking function is defined as
the similarity between the query and
the document.
One well known example in this
case is vector space model,
which we will cover more in
detail later in the lecture.
The second kind of models
are called probabilistic models.
In this family of models,
we follow a very different strategy.
While we assume that queries and
documents are all observations
from random variables, and
we assume there is a binary
random variable called R here,
to indicate whether a document
is relevant to a query.
We then define the score of document with
respect to a query as is a probability
that this random variable R is equal to 1,
given a particular document and query.
There are different cases
of such a general idea.
One is classic probabilistic model,
another is language model, yet
another is
divergence-from-randomness model.
In a later lecture,
we will talk more about the, one case,
which is language model.
The third kind of models of this
is probabilistic inference.
So here the idea is to associate
uncertainty to inference rules.
And we can then quantify the probability
that we can show that the query
follows from the document.
Finally, there is also a family of models
that are using axiomatic thinking.
Here the idea is to define
a set of constraints that
we hope a good retrieval
function to satisfy.
So in this case the problem is you seek
a good ranking function that can
satisfy all the desired constraints.
Interestingly, although these different
models are based on different thinking,
in the end the retrieval function
tends to be very similar.
And these functions tend to
also involve similar variables.
So now let's take a look at the, the
common form of a state of that retrieval
model and examine some of the common
ideas used in all these models.
First, these models are all
based on the assumption
of using bag of words for
representing text.
And we explained this in the natural
language processing lecture.
Bag of words representation remains
the main representation used in all
the search engines.
So, with this assumption,
the score of a query like a presidential
campaign news,
with respect to a document d here,
would be based on scores computed at,
based on each individual word.
And that means the score would
depend on the score of each word,
such as presidential, campaign, and news.
Here we can see there are three
different components,
each corresponding to how well the
document matches each of the query words.
Inside of these functions,
we see a number of heuristics views.
So for example, one factor that
affects the function g here is how
many times does the word
presidential occur in the document?
This is called a Term Frequency or TF.
We might also denote as
c of presidential and d.
In general if the word
occurs more frequently in
the document then the value of
this function would be larger.
Another factor is how
long is the document, and
this is so
to use the document length for score.
In general, if a term occurs in a long
document that many times,
it's not as significant as
if it occurred the same number
of times in a short document.
Because in the long document any term
is expected to occur more frequently.
Finally, there is this factor called
a document frequency, and that is we also
want to look at how often presidential
occurs in the entire collection.
And we call this Document Frequency,
or DF, of presidential.
And in some other models we
might also use a probability
to characterize this information.
So here, I show the probability of
presidential in the collection.
So all these are trying to
characterize the popularity of
the term in the collection.
In general,
matching a rare term in the collection
is contributing more to the overall
score then matching a common term.
So this captures some of the main ideas
used in pretty much all the state of
the art retrieval models.
So now, a natural question is
which model works the best?
Now, it turns out that many models work
equally well, so here I listed the four
major models that are generally regarded
as a state of the art retrieval models.
Pivoted length normalization,
BM25, query likelihood, PL2.
When optimized these models tend
to perform similarly and this was,
discussed in detail in this reference
at the end of this lecture.
Among all these,
BM25 is probably the most popular.
It's most likely that this has been used
in virtually all the search engines,
and you will also often see this
method discussed in research papers.
And we'll talk more about this
method later in some other lectures.
So, to summarize, the main points made
in this lecture are, first the design
of a good ranking function pre-requires a
computational definition of relevance, and
we achieve this goal by designing
a proper retrieval model.
Second, many models are equally effective
but we don't have a single winner here.
Researchers are still actively
working on this problem,
trying to find a truly
optimal retrieval model.
Finally, the state of the art
ranking functions tend to rely on
the following ideas.
First, bag of words representation.
Second, TF and
the document frequency of words.
Such information is used when
ranking function to determine
the overall contribution of matching
a word, and document length.
These are often combined in
interesting ways and we'll discuss
how exactly they are combined to rank
documents in the lectures later.
There are two suggested additional
readings if you have time.
The first is a paper where you can
find a detailed discussion and
comparison of multiple
state of the art models.
The second, is a book with a chapter
that gives a broad review of
different retrieval models.
[MUSIC]