[SOUND]
In this lecture, we continue
the discussion of Vector Space Model.
In particular, we are going to
talk about the TF transformation.
In the previous lecture,
we have derived a TF-IDF weighting
formula using the vector space model.
And we have shown that this model
actually works pretty well for
these examples as shown on
this slide except for d5,
which has received a very high score.
Indeed, it has received the highest
score among all these documents.
But this document is intuitively
non-relevant, so this is not desirable.
In this lecture, we're going to
talk about how would you use TF
transformation to solve this problem.
Before we discuss the details,
let's take a look at the formula for
this symbol here for
IDF weighting ranking function and
see why this document has
received such a high score.
So this is the formula, and
if you look at the formula carefully,
then you will see it involves a sum
over all the matched query terms.
And inside the sum, each matched
query sum has a particular weight.
And this weight is TF-IDF weighting.
So it has an IDF component
where we see 2 variables.
One is the total number of documents
in the collection, and that is m.
The other is the documentive frequency.
This is the number of documents
that contain this word w.
The other variables in,
involving the formula,
include the count of the query term.
W in the query, and
the count of the word in the document.
If you look at this document again,
now it's not hard to
realize that the reason why it has
received a high score is because
it has a very high count of campaign.
So the count of campaign in this document
is a four, which is much higher than
the other documents, and has contributed
to the high score of this document.
So intriguingly, in order to lower
the score for this document, we need
to somehow restrict the contribution of,
the matching of this term in the document.
And if you think about the matching of
terms in the document carefully you
actually would realize we
probably shouldn't reward
multiple occurrences so generously.
And by that I mean the first occurrence
of a term says a lot about the,
the matching of this term,
because it goes from zero count
to a count of one, and
that increase means a lot.
Once we see a word in the document,
it's very likely that the document
is talking about this word.
If we see an extra occurrence
on top of the first occurrence,
that is to go from one to two,
then we also can say that well, the second
occurrence kind of confirmed that it's
not a accidental mention of the word.
Now, we are more sure that this
document is talking about this word.
But imagine we have seen, let's say,
50 times of the word in the document.
Then, adding one extra occurrence
is not going to test more about
evidence because we are already sure
that this document is about this word.
So if you're thinking
this way it seems that
we should restrict the contributing
of a high account of term.
And that is the idea of TF Transformation.
So this transformation function is
going to turn the raw count of word
into a Term Frequency Weight,
for the word in the document.
So here I show in x-axis, that raw count,
and in y-axis I show
the Term Frequency Weight.
So, in the previous ranking functions
we actually have increasingly,
used some kind of transformation.
So for example in the zero-one bit
vector retentation we actually use
the Suchier transformation
function as shown here.
Basically if the count is
zero then it has zero weight.
Otherwise it would have a weight of one.
It's flat.
Now what about using
Term Count as a TF weight.
Well that's a linear function, right?
So it has just exactly
the same weight as the count.
Now we have just seen that
this is not desirable.
So what we want is something like this.
So for example with a logarithm function,
we can have a sub-linear
transformation that looks like this.
And this will control the influence of
really high weight because it's going to
lower its inference, yet it will
retain the inference of small count.
Or we might want to even bend the curve
more by applying logarithm twice.
Now people have tried all these methods
and they are indeed working better than
the linear form of the transformation,
but so far what works the best
seems to be this special transformation
called a BM25 transformation.
BM stands for best matching.
Now in this transformation,
you can see there's a parameter k here.
And this k controls the upper
bound of this function.
It's easy to see this function has
a upper bound because if you look at
the x divided by x plus k where
k is not an active number,
then the numerator will never be able
to exceed the denominator, right?
So, it's upper bounded by k plus 1.
Now, this is also difference between
this transformation function and
the logarithm transformation.
Which it doesn't have upperbound.
Now furthermore, one interesting property
of this function is that as we vary K,
we can actually simulate different
transformation functions,
including the two extremes
that are shown here.
That is a zero one bit transformation,
and the unit transformation.
So for example, if we set k to zero,
now you can see
the function value would be one.
So we precisely,
recover the zero one bit transformation.
If you set k to a very large number,
on the other hand,
other hand, it's going to look more
like the linear transformation function.
So in this sense,
this transformation is very flexible,
it allows us to control
the shape of the transformation.
It also has a nice property
of the upper bound.
And this upper bound is useful to control
the inference of a particular term.
And so that we can prevent a, a spammer
from just increasing the count of
1 term to spam all queries
that might match this term.
In other words this upper bound
might also ensure that all terms
will be counted when we aggregate the,
the weights, to compute a score.
As I said, this transformation
function has worked well, so far.
So to summarise this lecture,
the main point is that we need to do
some sub linearity of TF Transformation.
And this is needed to capture
the intuition of diminishing return from
high Term Counts.
It's also to avoid a dominance by
one single term over all others.
This BM25 Transformation, Transformation
that we talked about is very interesting.
It's so far one of the best performing
TF Transforming formation formulas.
It has upper bound, and
it's also robust and effective.
Now, if we're plug in this
function into our TF-IDF weighting
vector space model then we would
end up having the following
ranking function,
which has a BM25 TF component.
Now this is already very close to a state
of the art ranking function called a BM25.
And we will discuss how we can further
improve this formula in the next lecture.
[MUSIC]