[SOUND].
This lecture is about how to do fast
research by using inverted index.
In this lecture,
we are going to continue the discussion
of the system implementation.
In particular, we're going to talk about,
to how to support a faster
search by using inverted index.
So, let's think about what a general
scoring function might look like.
Now, of curse the vector space
model is a special case of this.
But we can imagine many other
retrieval functions of the same form.
So, the form of this
function is as follows.
We see this scoring
function of document d, and
query q is defined as first, a function
of f a that's adjustment in the function.
That what consider two
factors that are shown
here at the end, f sub d of d,
and f sub q of q.
These are adjustment factors
of a document and query, so
they're at the level of document,
and query.
So, and
then inside of this function we also see
there's a another function called edge.
So, this is the main part of
the scoring function,
and these as I just said
of the scoring factors at the level
of the whole document, and the query.
For example, document and
this aggregate function would
then combine all these.
Now, inside this h function,
there are functions that would compute
the weights of the contribution
of a matched query term t i.
So, this this g, the function g gives us
the weight of a matched query
term t i in document d.
And this h function with that
aggregate all these weights, so
it were, for example, take a sum, but
it of all the matched query in that terms.
But it can also be a product, or
could be another way of aggregate them.
And then finally, this adjustment
function would then consider
the document level, or query level
factors through further adjuster score,
for example, document lens [INAUDIBLE].
So, this general form would cover
many state of original functions.
Let's look at how we can score such
score documents with such
a function using inverted index.
So here's the general algorithm
that works as follows.
First these these Query level and
document level factors can be
pre-computed in the indexing term.
Of course, for the query,
we have to compute it as a query term.
But for document, for example,
document can be pre-computed.
And then we maintain a score accumulator
for each document d to compute the h.
And h is aggregation function
of all the matching query terms.
So how do we do that?
Well, for each query term,
we going to do fetch inverted list,
from the inverted index.
This will give us all the documents
that match this query term,
and that includes d1,
f1, and so, d and fn.
So each pair is document id and
the frequency of the term in the document.
Then for each entry d sub j and f sub j,
a particular match of the term in
this particular document d sub j,
we're going to computer the function g.
That would give us something like
a t of i, ef weights of this term.
So, we're computing the weight
contribution of matching this query term
in this document.
And then we're going to update the score
accumulator for this document.
And this would allow us to
add this to our accumulator,
that would incrementally
compute function h.
So this is basically a general
way to allow sort of computer
all functions of this form,
by using inverted index.
Note that we don't have to
attach any document that that
didn't match any query term,
but this is why it's fast.
We only need to process the documents that
tap, that match at least one query term.
In the end, then we're going to
adjust the score to compute a,
this function f of a and then we can sort.
So let's take a look at
the specific example.
In this, case let's assume the scoring
function's a very simple one.
It just takes us sum of tf, the rule of
tf, the count of, of term in the document.
Now this simple equation with the help
showing the algorithm clearly.
It's very easy to extend the,
the computation to include other weights
like the transformation of TF or
document or IDF weighting.
So let's take a look at specific example
with the query's information security,
and shows some entries of
the inverted index on the right side.
Information occurring before documents and
the frequencies is also there,
security is coding three documents.
So, let's see how the algorithm works,
all right?
So, first we iterate all the query terms,
and we fetch the first query then.
What is that?
That's information.
Right?
So, and imagine we have all these score
accumulators to score, score the,
score the scores for these documents.
We can imagine there will be allocated,
but
then they will only be
allocated as needed.
So before we do any weighting of terms
we don't even need a score accumulators.
But conceptual we have these score
accumulators eventually allocated, right?
So let's fetch the,
the entries from the inverted list for
information first, that's the first one.
So these score accumulators obviously
would be initialized as zeros.
So the first entry is d1 and 3,
3 is occurrences of
information in this document.
Since our scoring function assume that the
score is just a sum of these raw counts.
We just need to add a 3 to the score
accumulator to account for
the increase of score, due to matching
this term information, a document d1.
And now we go to the next entry.
That's d2 and 4 and then we'll add
a 4 to the score accumulator of d2.
Of course, at this point we will allocate
the score accumulator as needed.
And so, at this point, we have located
d1 and d2, and the next one is d3.
And we add 1, or we locate another score
coming in the spot d3 and add 1 to it.
And finally,
the d4 gets a 5 because the information
the term information occurred ti
in five times in this document.
Okay, so this completes the processing
of all the entries in the,
inverted index for information.
It's processed all the contributions
of matching information in this
four documents.
So now our arrows will go to the next
query term, that's security.
So, we're going to factor all
the inverted index entries for security.
So in this case, there were three entries.
And we're going to go
through each of them.
The first is d2 and 3.
And that means security occurred
three times in d2, and what do we do?
Well, we do exactly the same as
what we did for information.
So this time we're going
to do change the score,
accumulating d2 sees
it's already allocate.
And what we do is we'll add 3 to
the existing value which is a 4,
so we now get the 7 for d2.
D2 sc, score is increased because of the
match both information and the security.
Go to the next step entry, that's d4 and
1, so we've updated the score for
d4,and again we add 1 to d4,
so d4 goes from 5 to 6.
Finally we process d5 and 3.
SInce we have not yet
equated a score accumulator d4 to d5,
at this point, we allocate one,
45 and we're going to add 3 to it.
So, those scores on the last row
are the final scores for these documents.
If our scoring function is just a,
a simple sum of tf values.
Now what if we actually would like to,
to do lands normalization.
Well we can do the normalization
at this point for each document.
So to summarize this,
all right so you can see we first
processed the information determine
query term information, and
we process all the entries in
the inverted index for this term.
Then we process the security,
all right, let's think about
the what should be the order of processing
here when we consider query terms?
It might make difference,
especially if we don't want to keep
to keep all the score accumulators.
Let's say we only want to keep
the most promising score accumulators.
What do you think it would be
a good order to go through?
Would you go would you process
a common term first or
would you process a rare term first?
The answer is we should go through we
should process the rare term first.
A rare term will match fewer documents and
then the score confusion will be higher,
because the IDF value will be higher and,
and
then it allows us to attach
the most diplomacy documents first.
So it helps pruning some non
promising ones, if we don't need so
many documents to be returned to the user.
And so those are heuristics for
further improving the accuracy.
Here can also see how we can
incorporate the idea of weighting.
All right.
So they can [INAUDIBLE] when we
incorporated a one way process each
query term.
When we fetch in word index we
can fetch the document frequency,
and then we can compute the IDF.
Or maybe perhapsIDF value has already been
pre-computed when we index the document.
At that time we already computed the IDF
value that we can just fetch it.
So all these can be down at this time.
So that will mean one will process
all the entries for information these
these weights would be adjusted by the
same IDF, which is IDF for information.
So this is the basic idea of using
inverted index for faster search, and
works well for all kinds of formulas that
are of the general form and this generally
cov, the general form covers actually most
state of the art retrieval functions.
So there are some tricks to further
improve the efficiency ,some general mac
tech, techniques include caching.
This is just a to store some
results of popular query's, so
that next time when you see the same query
you simply return the stored results.
Similarly, you can also score the missed
of inverted index in the memory for
popular term.
And if the query comes
popular you will assume
it will fetch the inverted index for
the same term again.
So keeping that in the memory would help.
And these are general techniques for
improving efficiency.
We can also only keep the most promising
accumulators because a user generally
doesn't want to examine so many documents.
We only want to return high quality
subset of documents that likely ranked
on the top, in,in for that purpose
we can then prune the accumulators.
We don't have to store
all the accumulators.
At some point we just keep
the highest value accumulators.
Another technique is to do parallel
processing, and that's needed for
really processing such a large data set,
like the web data set.
And to scale up to the Web-scale
we need to special
to have the special techniques
to do parallel processing and
to distribute the storage of
files on multiple machines.
So here as a, here is a list of
some text retrieval toolkits.
It's, it's not a complete list.
You can find the more information
at this URL on the bottom.
Here I listed four here,
lucene is one of the most popular toolkit
that can support a lot of applications.
And it has very nice support for
applications.
You can use it to build
a search engine very quickly,
the downside is that it's not
that easy to extend it, and
the algorithms incremented there
are not the most advanced algorithms.
Lemur or Indri is another toolkit that
that does not have such a nice
support application as Lucene.
But it has many advanced
search algorithms.
And it's also easy to extend.
Terrier is yet another toolkit
that also has good support for
quotation capability and
some advanced algorithms.
So that's maybe in between Lemur,
or Lucene or
maybe rather combining the strands of
both, so that's also useful toolkit.
MeTA is the toolkit that we'll use for
the programming assignment,
and this is a new toolkit
that has a combination
of both text retrieval algorithms and
text mining algorithms.
And so, toolkit models are implement, they
are, there are a number of text analysis
algorithms, implemented in the toolkit,
as well as basic research algorithms.
So, to summarize all the discussion
about the system implementation,
here are the major take away points.
Inverted index is the primary data
structure for supporting a search engine.
That's the key to enable faster
response to a user's query.
And the basic idea is process that,
pre-process the data as much as we can,
and we want to do compression
when appropriate.
So that we can save disk space and
can speed up IO and
processing of the inverted
index in general.
We'll talk about how we will construct
the inverted index when the data
can fit into the memory.
And then we talk about faster search using
inverted index, basically to exploit
the inverted index to accumulate scores
for documents matching a query term.
And we exploit Zipf's law
avoid touching many documents
that don't match any query term.
And this algorithm can, can support
a wide range of ranking algorithms.
So these basic techniques have mm,
have great potential for further scanning
output using distribution to withstand
parallel processing and the caching.
Here are two additional readings that
you can take a look at if you have time,
and are interested in
learning more about this.
The first one is a classic textbook on the
scare the efficiency of inverted index and
the compression techniques,
and how to in general,
build a efficient search engine in
terms of the space overhead and speed.
The second one is a newer textbook that
has a nice discussion of implementing and
evaluating search engines.
[MUSIC]