[NOISE].
>> This lecture is about some practical
issues that you would have to address in
evaluation of text retrieval systems.
In this lecture we will continue
the discussion of evaluation.
We will cover some practical
issues that you will have to solve
in actual evaluation of
text retrieval systems.
So, in order to create a test collection,
we have to create a set of queries,
a set of documents and
a set of relevance judgments.
It turns out that each is
actually challenging to create.
So first, the documents and
queries must be representative.
They must rep, represent the real queries
and real documents that the users handle.
And we also have to use many queries and
many documents in order to
avoid biased conclusions.
For the matching of relevant
documents with the queries,
we also need to ensure that there exists a
lot of relevant documents for each query.
If a query has only one that is a relevant
document in the collection then, you know,
it's not very informative to
compare different methods
using such a query because there is not
much room for us to see difference.
So, ideally there should be more
relevant documents in the collection.
But yet the queries also should represent
real queries that we care about.
In terms of relevance judgements, the
challenge is to ensure complete judgements
of all the documents for all the queries,
yet, minimizing human and fault.
Because we have to use the human
labor to label these documents.
It's very labor intensive.
And as a result, it's impossible to
actually label all of the documents for
all the queries, especially considering
a joint, data set like the web.
So, this is actually a major challenge.
It's a very difficult challenge.
For measures, it's also challenging
because what we want with measures is that
with accuracy reflected
the perceived utility of users.
We have to consider carefully
what the users care about and
then design measures to measure that.
If we, your measure is not
measuring the right thing,
then your conclusion would,
would be misled.
So it's very important.
So we're going to talk
about a couple issues here.
One is the statistical significance test,
and
this also is the reason why we
have to use a lot of queries, and
the question here is how sure can you
be that I observed the difference?
It doesn't simply result from
the particular queries you choose.
So here are some sample results of
average precision for System A and
System B in two different experiments.
And you can see in the bottom,
we have mean average position, all right?
So the mean,
if you look at the mean average position
the mean average positions are exactly
the same in both experiments.
All right, so you can see this is 0.2,
this is 0.4 for
system B and
again here its also 0.2 and 0.4.
So they are identical.
Yet if you look at the, these exact
average positions for different queries,
if you look at these numbers in detail,
you will realize that in one case
you would feel that you can trust
the conclusion here given by the average.
In another case, in the other case,
you will feel that, well, I'm not sure.
So, why don't you take a look at
all these numbers for a moment.
Pause the video.
So, if you at the average,
the main average position,
we can easily say that, well,
System B is better, right?
So it's, after all, it's 0.4 and
then this is twice as much as 0.2.
So that's a better performance.
But if you look at these two experiments
and look at the detailed results,
you will see that we'll be more
confident to say that in the case one.
In experiment one.
In this case because these numbers seem to
be consistently better than for system B.
Where as in, experiment two,
we're not sure.
because, looking at some results,
like this, after system A is better.
And this is another case
where system A is better.
But yet, if we look at on the average,
System B is better.
So what do you think?
You know, how reliable is our conclusion
if we only look at the average?
Now in this case, intuitively, we feel
it's better than one, it's more reliable.
But how can we quantitatively
answer this question?
And this is why we need to do
statistical significance test.
So the idea of a statistical significance
test is basically to assess the vary,
variance across these different queries.
If there's a, a big variance that means
that the results could fluctuate
a lot according to different queries.
Then we should believe that
unless you have used a lot of
queries the results might change
if we use another set of queries.
Right?
So, this is then not so
if you have seen high variance
then it's not very reliable.
So let's look at these results
again in the second case.
So here we show two,
different ways to compare them.
One is a Sign Test.
And we'll, we'll just look at the sign.
If System B is better than System A,
then we have a plus sign.
When System A is better
we have a minus sign etc.
Using this case if you see this,
well, there are seven cases.
We actually have four cases
where System B is better.
But three cases System A is better.
You know intuitively,
this is almost like random results.
Right, so if you just take a random
sample of to, to flip seven coins,
and if you use plus to denote the head and
then minus to denote the tail, and
that could easily be the results of just
randomly flipping, these seven coins.
So, the fact that the, the average
is larger doesn't tell us anything.
You know, we can't reliably concur that.
And this can be quantitative
in the measure by, a p value.
And that basically, means,
the probability that this result is
in fact from random fluctuation.
In this case, probability is one.
It means it surely is
a random fluctuation.
Now in Wilcoxon, test,
it's a non parametrical test,
and we would be not only
looking at the signs
we'll be also looking at
the magnitude of the difference.
But, we, we, we can draw a similar
conclusion where you say well it's
very likely to be from random.
So to illustrate this let's
think about such a distribution.
And this is called a normal distribution.
We assume that the mean is zero here.
Let's say, well, we started with
the assumption that there's no difference
between the two systems.
But we assume that because of random
fluctuations depending on the queries
we might observe a difference, so
the actual difference might be
on the left side here or
on the right side here, right?
And, and
this curve kind of shows the probability
that we would actually observe values
that are deviating from zero here.
Now, so if we, look at this picture then
we see that if a difference
is observed here,
then the chance is very
high that this is in fact,
a random observation, right.
We can define region of you know, likely
observation because of random fluctuation.
And this is 95% of all outcomes.
And in this interval
then the observed values
may still be from random fluctuation.
But if you observe a value in this
region or a difference on this side,
then the difference is unlikely
from random fluctuation.
Right, so there is a very small
probability that you will observe
such a difference just because
of random fluctuation.
So in that case, we can then conclude
the difference must be real.
So System B is indeed better.
So, this is the idea of
the statistical significance test.
The takeaway message here is that
you have used many queries to avoid
jumping into a conclusion as in this
case to say System B is better.
There are many different ways of doing
this statistical significance test.
So now, let's talk about the other
problem of making judgements and
as we said earlier,
it's very hard to judge all the documents
completely unless it is a small data set.
So the question is, if we can't
afford judging all the documents
in the collection,
which subset should we judge?
And the solution here is pooling.
And this is a strategy that has been used
in many cases to solve this problem.
So the idea of pulling is the following.
We would first choose a diverse
set of ranking methods,
these are types of retrieval systems.
And we hope these methods
can help us nominate
likely relevance in the documents.
So the goal is to pick out
the relevant documents..
It means we are to make judgements
on relevant documents because those
are the most useful documents
from the users perspective.
So, that way we would have each
to return top-K documents.
And the K can vary from systems, right.
But the point is to ask them to suggest
the most likely relevant documents.
And then we simply combine
all these top-K sets to form
a pool of documents for
human assessors to judge.
So, imagine you have many systems.
Each will return K documents, you know,
take the top-K documents, and
we form the unit.
Now, of course there are many
documents that are duplicated,
because many systems might have
retrieved the same random documents.
So there will be some duplicate documents.
And there are,
there are also unique documents that are
only returned by one system, so the idea
of having diverse set of result ranking
methods is to ensure the pool is broad.
And can include as many possible
random documents as possible.
And then the users with
the human assessors would make
complete the judgements on this data set,
this pool.
And the other unjudged documents are
usually just a assumed to be non-relevant.
Now if the pool is large enough,
this assumption is okay.
But the, if the pool is not very large,
this actually has to be reconsidered,
and we might use other
strategies to deal with them and
there are indeed other
methods to handle such cases.
And such a strategy is generally okay for
comparing systems that
contribute to the pool.
That means if you participate in
contributing to the pool then it's
unlikely that it will penalize
your system because the top
ranked documents have all been judged.
However, this is problematic for
even evaluating a new system that may
not have contributed to the pool.
In this case, you know, a new system
might be penalized because it might have
nominated some relevant documents
that have not been judged.
So those documents might be
assumed to be non-relevant.
And that, that's unfair.
So to summarize the whole part
of text retrieval evaluation,
it's extremely important because the
problem is an empirically defined problem.
If we don't rely on users, there's no way
to tell whether one method works better.
If we have inappropriate
experiment design,
we might misguide our research or
applications.
And we might just draw wrong conclusions.
And we have seen this in
some of our discussion.
So, make sure to get it right for
your research or application.
The main methodology is Cranfield
evaluation methodology and
this is near the main paradigm used in
all kinds of empirical evaluation tasks,
not just a search engine variation.
Map and nDCG are the two main measures
that should definitely know about and
they are appropriate for
comparing ranking algorithms.
You will see them often
in research papers.
Perceiving up to ten documents is easier
to interpret from users perspective.
So, that's also often useful.
What's not covered is some other
evaluation strategy like A-B test
where the system would mix two of
the results of two methods randomly.
And then will show the mix
of results to users.
Of course, the users don't see
which result is from which method.
The users would judge those results or
click on those those documents in
in a search engine application.
In this case, then, the search engine can
keep track of the clicked documents, and
see if one method has contributed
more to the clicked documents.
If the user tends to click on
one the results from one method,
then it's just that method may,
may be better.
So this is what leverages a real users
of a search engine to do evaluation.
It's called A-B Test, and
it's a strategy that's often used by
the modern search engines,
the commercial search engines.
Another way to evaluate IR or
text retrieval is user studies,
and we haven't covered that.
I've put some references here that you can
look at if you want to
know more about that.
So there are three
additional readings here,
these are three mini
books about evaluation.
And they are all excellent in covering a
broad review of information retrieval and
evaluation.
And this covered some of
the things that we discussed.
But they also have a lot
of others to offer.
[MUSIC]