[SOUND] This lecture is about
the implementation of
text retrieval systems.
In this lecture, we will discuss how we
can implement a text retrieval method
to build a search engine.
The main challenge is to
manage a lot of text data and
to enable a query to be answered very
quickly and to respond to many queries.
This is a typical text
retrieval system architecture.
We can see the documents
are first processed by a tokenizer
to get tokenizer units, for example words.
And then these words or
tokens would be processed by
an indexer that would create an index,
which is a data structure for the search
engine to use to quickly answer a query.
And the query will be going
through a similar processing step.
So, the tokenizer will be
apprised to query as well so
that the text can be
processed in the same way.
The same units will be
matched with each other.
And the query's representation
will then be given to the scorer.
Which would use a index to
quickly answer a user's query by
scoring the documents and
then ranking them.
The results will be given to the user.
And then the user can look at the results
and and provide some feedback that can be
expressed judgements about which documents
are good, which documents are bad,
or implicit feedback such as pixels so the
user doesn't have to any, anything extra.
The user will just look at the results and
skip some and
click on some results to view.
So these interaction signals can be used
by the system to improve the ranking
accuracy by assuming that viewed documents
are better than the skipped ones.
So, a search engine system then
can be divided into three parts.
The first part is the indexer, and
the second part is the scorer,
that responds to the user's query.
And the third part is
the feedback mechanism.
Now typically, the indexer is done in
the offline manner so you can pre-process
the correct data and to build the inverter
index which we will introduce in a moment.
And this data structure can then be used
by the online module which is a scorer
to process a user's query dynamically and
quickly generate search results.
The feedback mechanism can be done online
or offline depending on the method.
The implementation of the index and
the, the scorer is fairly standard,
and this is the main topic of this
lecture and the next few lectures.
The feedback mechanism,
on the other hand has variations.
It depends on what method is used.
So that is usually done in
a algorithm-specific way.
Let's first talk about the tokenize.
Tokenization is a normalize lexical
units into the same form so
that semantically similar words
can be matched with each other.
Now in the language of English
stemming is often used and
this what map all the inflectional
forms of words into the same root form.
So for example, computer computation and
computing can all be matched
to the root form compute.
This way, all these different forms of
computing can be matched with each other.
Normally this is a good idea to increase
the coverage of documents that
are matched with this query.
But it's also not always beneficial
because sometimes the subtlest
difference between computer and
computation might still suggest the
difference in the coverage of the content.
But in most cases,
stemming seems to be beneficial.
When we tokenize the text in some other
languages, for example Chinese, we might
face some special challenges in segmenting
the text to find the word boundaries.
Because it's not ob,
obvious where the boundary is as
there's no space separating them.
So, here, of course,
we have to use some language-specific
natural language processing techniques.
Once we do tokenization, then we would
index the text documents, and that it
will convert the documents into some data
structure that can enable fast search.
The basic idea is to precompute
as much as we can, basically.
So the most commonly used index
is called a inverted index.
And this has been used, to,
in many search engines to
support basic search algorithms.
Sometimes other indices, for
example a document index,
might be needed in order to support a,
a feedback.
Like I said, this, this kind of
techniques are not really standard
in that they vary a lot according
to the feedback methods.
To understand why we
are using inverted index.
It will be useful for you to think
about how you would respond to
a single term query quickly.
So if you want to use more time to
think about that, pause the video.
So think about how you can
preprocess the text data so
that you can quickly respond
to a query with just one word.
Well, if you have thought about question,
you might realize that where the best is
to simply create a list of documents
that match every term in the vocabulary.
In this way, you can basically
pre-construct the answers.
So when you see a term,
you can simply just fetch
the ranked list of documents for
that term and return the list to the user.
So that's the fastest way to
respond to single term query.
Now the idea of invert index is
actually basically like that.
We can do, pre-construct such a index.
That would allow us to quickly find the,
all the documents that
match a particular term.
So let's take a look at this example.
We have three documents here, and
these are the documents that you
have seen in some previous lectures.
Suppose we want to create invert index for
these documents, then we will
need to maintain a dictionary.
In the dictionary we'll have one entry for
each term.
And we're going to store some
basic statistics about the term.
For example, the number of
documents that match the term or
the total number of, fre,
total frequency of the term,
which means we would encounter
duplicated occurrences of the term.
And so, for example, news.
This term occurred in
all the three documents.
So the count of documents is three.
And you might also realize we needed
this count of documents or document
frequency for computing some statistics
to be used in the vector space model.
Can you think of that?
So, what waiting heuristic
would need this count?
Well, that's the IDF, right,
inverse document frequency.
So IDF is a property of the term,
and we can compute it right here.
So with the document account here,
it's easy to compute the IDF either at
this time or when we build an index or.
At running time when we see a query.
Now in addition to these
basic statistics we also
saw all the documents that matched news.
And these entries are stored
in a file called a Postings.
So in this case it matched 3 documents and
we store Information about
these 3 documents here.
This is the document id,
document 1, and the frequency is 1.
The TF is 1 for news.
In the second document it's also 1, etc.
So from this list that we can get all
the documents that match the term news.
And we can also know the frequency
of news in these documents.
So, if the query has just one word,
news, and
we can easily look up in this
table to find the entry and
go quickly to the postings to fetch
all the documents that match news.
So, let's take a look at another term.
Now this time let's take a look
at the word presidential.
All right, this word occurred
in only 1 document, document 3.
So, the document frequency is 1, but
it occurred twice in this document.
And so the frequency count is 2, and
the frequency count is used for,
in some other retrieval method
where we might use the frequency
to assess the popularity of a,
a term in the collection.
And similarly, we'll have a pointer
to the postings, right here.
And in this case there is
only one entry here because
the term occurred in just one document.
And that's here.
The document id is 3,
and it occurred twice.
So this is the basic
idea of inverted index.
It's actually pretty simple, right?
With this structure we can easily fetch
all the documents that match a term.
And this will be the basis for
storing documents for our query.
Now sometimes we also want to store
the positions of these terms.
So, in many of these
cases the term occurred
just once in the document so there's only
one position, for example in this case.
But in this case the term occurred
twice so it would store two positions.
Now the position information is
very useful for checking whether
the matching of query terms is actually
within a small window of, let's say,
five words, or ten words,
or whether the matching of,
the two query terms,
is in fact a phrase of two words.
This can all be checked quickly by
using the position information.
So why is inverted index good for
faster search?
Well we just talked about the possibility
of using the two ends
of a single-word query.
And that's very easy.
What about a multiple-term queries?
Well, let's look at the,
some special cases of the Boolean query.
A Boolean query is basically
a Boolean expression, like this.
So I want the relevant document
to match both term A AND term B.
All right, so
that's one conjunctive query.
Or, I want the relevant documents
to match term A OR term B.
That's a disjunctive query.
Now how can we answer such
a query by using inverted index?
Well if you think a, a bit about it,
it would be obvious.
Because we have simply to fetch all
the documents that match term A and
also fetch all the documents
that match term B.
And then just take the intersection
to answer a query like A and B.
Or to take the union to
answer the query A or B.
So this is all very easy to answer.
It's going to be very quick.
Now what about the multi-term
keyword query?
We talked about the vector space model for
example.
And we would match such a query with
a document and generate a score.
And the score is based on
aggregated term weights.
So in this case it's not a Boolean query,
but
the scoring can be actually
done in a similar way.
Basically it's similar to
disjunctive Boolean query.
Basically It's like A OR B.
We take the union of all the, documents
that matched at least one query term,
and then we would
aggregate the term weights.
So this is a, a, a basic idea of
using inverted index for
scoring documents in general.
And we're going to talk about
this in more detail later.
But for now,
let's just look at the question,
why is inverted index, a good idea?
Basically, why is it more efficient than
sequentially just scanning documents?
Right?
This is, the obvious approach.
You can just compute the score for
each document, and
then you can score them,
sorry, you can then sort them.
This is a, a straightforward method.
But this is going to be very slow.
Imagine the web.
It has a lot of documents.
If you do this, then it will take
a long time to answer your query.
So the question now is, why would the in,
the inverted index be much faster?
Well it has to do with
the word distribution in text.
So, here's some common phenomenon
of word distribution in text.
There are some language-in, independent
patterns that seem to be stable.
And these patterns are basically
characterized by the following pattern.
A few words like the common words
like the a, or we, occur very,
very frequently in text.
So they account for
a large percent of occurrences of words.
But most word would occur just rarely.
There are many words that occur just once,
let's say, in a document,
or once in the collection.
And there are many such single terms.
It's also true that the most
frequent words in one corpus
may actually be rare in another.
That means, although the general
phenomenon is applicable or
is observed in many cases,
the exact words that are common
may vary from context to context.
So this phenomena is characterized
by what's called a Zipf's Law.
This law says that the rank
of a word multiplied by,
the frequency of the word
is roughly constant.
So formally if we use F of
w to denote the, frequency,
r of w to denote the rank of a word,
then this is the formula.
It basically says the same thing,
just mathematical term, where C is,
basically a constant, right, so as, so.
And there is also
parameter alpha that might,
be adjusted to better fit
any empirical observations.
So if I plot the word
frequencies in sorted order,
then you can see this more easily.
The x-axis is basically the word rank.
And this is r of w.
And the y-axis is the word frequency,
or F of w.
Now, this curve basically shows
that the product of the two
is roughly the constant.
Now, if you look these words, we can see.
They can be separated into three group2s.
In the middle it's
the immediate frequency words.
These words tend to occur in
quite a few documents, right?
But they're not like those
most frequent words.
And they are also not very rare.
So they tend to be often used in in,
in queries.
And they also tend to have high TFI
diff weights in these intermediate
frequency words.
But if you look at the left
part of the curve.
These are the highest frequency words.
They occur very frequently.
They are usually stopper words,
the, we, of, et cetera.
Those words are very, very frequently.
They are, in fact,
a too frequently to be discriminated.
And they generally are not very
useful for, for retrieval.
So, they are often removed, and
this is called a stop words removal.
So you can use pretty much just the count
of words in the collection to kind
of infer what words might be stop words.
Those are basically
the highest frequency words.
And they also occupy a lot of
space in the invert index.
You can imagine the posting entries for
such a word would be very long.
And then therefore,
if you can remove such words,
you can save a lot of
space in the invert index.
We also show the tail part,
which is, has a lot of rare words.
Those words don't occur very frequently,
and there are many such words.
Those words are actually very useful for
search,
also, if a user happens to be
interested in such a topic.
But because they're rare it's
often true that users are,
aren't the necessary
interest in those words.
But retain them would allow us to
match such a document accurately,
and they generally have very high IDFs.
So what kind of data structures should
we use to to store inverted index?
Well, it has two parts, right?
If you recall we have a dictionary,
and we also have postings.
The dictionary has modest size,
although for
the web, it still wouldn't be very large.
But compared with postings, it's modest.
And we also need to have fast,
random access to the entries
because we want to look up
the query term very quickly.
So, therefore, we prefer to keep such
a dictionary in memory if it's possible.
Or, or, or if the connection is not
very large, and this is visible.
But if the connection is very large,
then it's in general not possible.
If the vocabulary size is very large,
obviously we can't do that.
So, but in general, that's our goal.
So the data structures
that we often use for
storing dictionary would be direct access
data structures, like a hash table or
B-tree if we can't store everything
in memory of the newest disk.
And but to try to build a structure that
would allow it to quickly look up our
entries.
Right.
For postings, they're huge, you can see.
And in general, we don't have to have
direct access to a specific engine.
We generally would just look up a,
a sequence of document IDs and
frequencies for all of the documents
that match a query term.
So we would read those
entries sequentially.
And therefore,
because it's large and we generate,
have store postings on disk,
so they have to stay on disk.
And they would contain information such
as document IDs, term frequencies, or
term positions, et cetera.
Now because they're very large,
compression is often desirable.
Now this is not only
to save disk space and
this is of course,
one benefit of compression.
It's not going to occupy that much space.
But it's also to help improving speed.
Can you see why?
Well, we know that input and
output will cost a lot of time in
comparison with the time taken by CPU.
So CPU is much faster.
But IO takes time.
And so by compressing the inverted index,
the posting files will become smaller.
And the entries that we
have to read into memory
to process a query done,
would would be smaller.
And then so we, we can reduce
the amount of traffic and IO.
And that can save a lot of time.
Of course, we have to then do
more processing of the data
when we uncompress the,
the data in the memory.
But as I said, CPU is fast, so
overall, we can still save time.
So compression here is both
to save disk space and
to speed up the loading
of the inverted index.
[MUSIC]