[SOUND] This lecture is about how to
evaluate the text retrieval system when
we have multiple levels of judgments.
In this lecture we will continue
the discussion of evaluation.
We're going to look at how to
evaluate the text retrieval system.
And we have multiple level of judgements.
So, so far we have talked
about binding judgements,
that means a documents is judged
as being relevant or not-relevant.
But earlier we will also talk about,
relevance as a matter of degree.
So we often can distinguish it
very higher relevant options,
those are very useful options, from you
know, lower rated relevant options.
They are okay, they are useful perhaps.
And further from non-relevant documents.
Those are not useful.
Right?
So imagine you can have ratings for
these pages.
Then you would have much
more levels of ratings.
For example, here I show an example
of three levels, three were relevant.
Sorry, three were very relevant.
Two for marginally relevant and
one for non-relevant.
Now how do we evaluate such a new system
using these judgements of use of the map
doesn't work, average of precision
doesn't work, precision and
record doesn't work because
they rely on vinyl judgement.
So let's look at the sum top regular
results when using these judgments.
Right?
Imagine the user would be mostly
care about the top ten results here.
Right.
And we mark the the rating levels or
relevance levels for
these documents as shown here.
Three, two, one, one, three, et cetera.
And we call these gain.
And the reason why we call it a gain,
is because the measure that
we are infusing is called, NTCG,
normalizer discount of accumulative gain.
So this gain basically can mesh your,
how much gain of random
information a user can obtain by
looking at each document, alright.
So looking after the first document
the user can gain three points.
Looking at the non-relevant document
the user would only gain one point.
Right.
Looking at the multi-level relevant or
marginally relevant document the user
would get two points et cetera.
So this gain usually matches the utility
of a document from a user's perspective.
Of course if we assume the user
stops at the ten documents, and
we're looking at the cutoff at ten we can
look after the total gain of the user.
And what's that,
well that's simply the sum of these and
we call it the cumulative gain.
So if we use a stops at
the positua that's just a three.
If the user looks at another
document that's a 3 plus 2.
If the user looks at the more documents.
Then the cumulative gain is more.
Of course, this is at the cost of
spending more time to examine the list.
So cumulative gain gives
us some idea about
how much total gain the user would have
if the user examines all these documents.
Now, in NDCG, we also have another letter
here, D, discounted cumulative gain.
So why do we want to do discounting?
Well, if you look at this cumulative gain,
there is one deficiency which is
it did not consider the rank
position of these these documents.
So, for example looking at the,
this sum here
and we only know there is only
one highly relevant document,
one marginally relevant document,
two non-relevant documents.
We don't really care
where they are ranked.
Ideally, we want these two
to be ranked on the top.
Which is the case here.
But how can we capture that intuition?
Well we have to say, well this 3 here
is not as good as this 3 on the top.
And that means the contribution of,
the game from different positions,
has to be weight by their position.
And this is the idea of discounting,
basically.
So, we're going to say, well, the first
one, doesn't it need to be discounted
because the user can be assume that
you always see this document, but
the second one,
this one will be discounted a little bit,
because there's a small possibility
that the user wouldn't notice it.
So, we divide this gain by the weight,
based on the position.
So, log of two, two is the rank
position of this document and,
when we go to the third position, we,
discount even more because the numbers
is log of three, and so on and so forth.
So when we take a such a sum then a lowly
ranked document would not contribute
contribute that much as
a highly ranked document.
So that means if you, for example,
switch the position of this and let's say
this position and this one, and then
you would get more discount if you put
for example, very relevant document
here as opposed to two here.
Imagine if you put the three here,
then it would have to be discounted.
So it's not as good as if you
would put the three here.
So this is the idea of discounting.
Okay, so n, now at this point that we have
got this discounted cumulative gain for
measuring the utility of this ranked
list with multiple levels of judgments.
So are we happy with this?
Well we can use this rank systems.
Now we still need to do
a little bit more in order to
make this measure comfortable
across different topics.
And this is the last step.
And by the way,
here we just show that DCG at the ten.
Alright.
So this is the total sum of DCG
over all these ten documents.
So the last step is called N,
normalization.
And if we do that then
we get normalized DCG.
So how do we do that?
Well, the idea here is
within the Normalized DCG
by the Ideal DCG at the same cutoff.
What is the Ideal DCG?
Well this is a DCG of ideal ranking.
So imagine if we have nine
documents in the whole collection
rated a three here and that means in
total we have nine documents rated three.
Then, our ideal ranked the Lister
would have put all these nine
documents on the very top.
So all these would have to be three and
then this would be followed by a two here,
because that's the best we could do
after we have run out of threes.
But all these positions would be threes.
Right?
So this would be our ideal ranked list.
And then we can compute the DCG for
this ideal rank list.
So this would be given by this
formula you see here, and so
this idea DCG would be used
as the normalizer DCG.
Like so here, and this IdealDCG
would be used as a normalizer.
So you can imagine now normalization
essentially is to compare the actual DCG
with the best decision you can
possibly get for this topic.
Now why do we want to do this?
Well by doing this we'll map the DCG
values in to a range of zero through one,
so the best value, or the highest
value for every query would be one.
That's when you're relevance
is in fact the idealist.
But otherwise in general
you will be lower than one.
Now what if we don't do that?
Well, you can see this transformation or
this numberization,
doesn't really affect the relative
comparison of systems for
just one topic, because this ideal
DCG is the same for all the systems.
So the ranking of systems based on
only DCG would be exactly the same.
As if you rank them based
on the normalized decision.
The difference however is when
we have multiple topics because
if we don't do normalization, different
topics will have different scales of DCG.
For a topic like this one we have
nine highly relevant documents.
The DCG can get really high.
But imagine that in another case there
are only two very relevant documents.
In total in the whole collection.
Then the highest DCG that
any system could achieve for
such a topic would not be very high.
So again we face the problem of different
scales of DCG values and when we
take an average we don't want the average
to be dominated by those high values.
Those are again easy quires.
So by doing the normalization we have all,
avoid the problem.
Making all the purists
contribute equal to the average.
So this is the idea of NDCG.
It's used for measuring relevance based
on much more level relevance judgments.
So more in the more general way,
this is basically a measure
that can be applied through
any ranked task with much more level of,
of judgments.
And the scale of
the judgments can be multiple
can be more than binary, not only more
than binary, they can be multiple levels,
like one's or five, or
even more depending on your application.
And the main idea of this
measure just to summarize,
is to measure the total utility
of the top k documents.
So you always choose a cutoff, and
then you measure the total utility.
And it would discount the contribution
from a lowly ranked document,
and finally, it would do normalization
to ensure comparability across queries
[MUSIC]