[SOUND].
This lecture is about
the Inverted Index Construction.
In this lecture, we will continue
the discussion of system implementation.
In particular, we're going to discuss
how to construct the inverted index.
The construction of the inverted index
is actually very easy if the data set is
very small.
It's very easy to construct a dictionary
and then store the postings in a file.
The problem's that when our data
is not able to fit to the memory,
then we have to use some
special method to deal with it.
And unfortunately, in most retrieval a
petitions, the data set would be large and
they generally cannot be,
loaded into the memory at once.
And there are many approaches
to solving that problem, and
sorting-based method, is quite common and
works in four steps as shown here.
First, we collect the the local termID,
document ID, and frequency tuples.
Basically, you overlook kinds of terms
in a small set of documents, and, and
then, once you collect those counts, you
can sort those counts based on terms so
that you build a local,
a partial inverted index.
And these are called, runs.
And then, you write them into
a temporary file on the disk.
And then, you merge in step three with do
pair-wise merging of these runs, and here,
you eventually merge all the runs,
we generate a single inverted index.
So this is an illustration of this method.
On the left, you see some documents.
And on the right, we have, show a term
lexicon and a document ID lexicon.
And these lexicon's are to map a stream
based representations of document IDs or
terms into integer representations.
Or, and, map back from,
integers to the screen representation.
And the reason why we want, are interested
in using integers represent these IDs,
is because,
integers are often easier to handle.
For example,
integers can be used as index for
array and they are also easy to compress.
So this is a, one reason why we,
tend to map these streams
into integers so that so that we don't
have to, carry these streams around.
So how does this approach work?
Well, it's very simple.
We're going to scan these
documents sequentially, and
then pause the documents and
a count the frequencies of terms.
And in this, stage we generally sort
the frequencies by document IDs because we
process each document that sequentially.
So, we first encounter all the terms in,
the first document.
Therefore, the document IDs,
are all once in this stage.
And so, and, this would be
followed by document IDs 2.
And, and they're naturally sort in this
order just because we process the data in
this order.
At some point, the,
we will run out of memory and
that would have to,
to write them into the disk.
But before we do that,
we're going to a sort them, just,
use whatever memory we have,
we can sort them, and
then, this time,
we're going to sort based on term IDs.
Note that here, we're using, this,
the term IDs as a key to sort.
So, all the entries that share the same
term would be grouped together.
In this case,
we can see all the, all the IDs
of documents that match term
one would be grouped together.
And we're going to write this into
the disk as a temporary file.
And that would, allow us to use the memory
to process the next batch of documents,
and we're going to do that for
all the documents.
So we're going to write a lot of
temporary files into the disk.
And then,
the next stage is to do merge sort.
Basically, we're going to,
merge them and the sort them.
Eventually, we will get a single
inverted index where the,
their entries are sorted
based on term IDs.
And on the top,
we can see these are the order entries for
the documents that match term ID 1.
So this is basically how we can do,
the construction of inverted index,
even though that they're or
cannot be, or loaded into the memory.
Now, we mentioned earlier that
because the po, postings are very large,
it's desirable to compress them.
So let's now talk a little bit about
how we compress inverted index.
Well, the idea of compression, in general,
is you leverage skewed
distributions of values.
And we generally have to use variable
lengths in coding instead of the fixed
lengths in coding as we', using,
by defaulting a program language like C++.
And so, how can we leverage the skewed
distributions of values to,
compress these values?
Well, in general, we would use fewer
bits to encode those frequent words
at a cost of using, longer bits from
the code than those, rare values.
So in our case, let's think about how
we can compress the tf, term frequency.
If you can picture what the inverted
index would look like and
you'll see in postings there are a lot of,
term frequencies.
Those are the frequencies of terms,
in all those documents.
Now, we, if you think about it, what
kind of values are most frequent there?
You probably will, be able to guess
that the small numbers tend to occur
far more frequently than large numbers.
Why?
Well, think of about
the distribution of words, and
this is due to Zipf's law and
many words occur just, rarely.
So we see a lot of small numbers,
therefore, we can use fewer bits for
the small, but highly frequent integers,
and at the cost of using more bits for
large integers.
This is a trade-off, of course.
If the values are distributed uniformly
and this won't save us any, spacing.
But because we tend to see many
small values, they're very frequent.
We can save on average
even though sometimes,
when we see a large number we
have to use a lot of bits.
What about the document IDs
that we also saw in postings.
Well, they are not,
distributed in a skewed way, right?
So, how can we deal with that?
Well, it turns out you can
use a trick called the d-gap,
and that, that is to store
the difference of these term IDs.
And we can, imagine if a term
has matched many documents,
then there will be a long
list of document IDs.
So when we take the gap, and when we take
difference between adjacent document IDs,
those gaps will be small.
So we'll again see a lot of small numbers,
whereas,
if a term occurred in only a few
documents, then the gap would be large.
The larger numbers will not be frequent,
so this creates some skewed distribution
that would allow us to,
to compress these values.
This is also possible because in order to
uncover or uncompress these document IDs,
we have to sequentially process the data
because we stored the difference.
And in order to recover the,
the exact document ID,
we have to first recover the previous
document ID, and then, we can add
the difference to the previous document ID
to restore the, the current document ID.
Now, this was possible because we
only needed to have sequential
access to those document IDs.
Once we look up a term we fetch all
the document IDs that match the term,
then we sequentially process them.
So it's very natural that's why this,
trick actually works.
And there are many different methods for
encoding.
So binary code is a common used code in,
in just any program.
Language that we use basically
a fixed length in coding.
Unary code and gamma code, and
delta code are all possible in this and
there are many other possible in this.
So let's look at some
of them in more detail.
Binary code is really
equal-length in coding.
And that's a property for
the randomly distributed values.
The unary coding is is a variable and
it's important [INAUDIBLE].
In this case, integer that is,
I've missed one or
we encode that as x minus 1,
1 bit followed by 0.
So for example, 3 would be encoded
as two 1s followed by a 0,
whereas 5 would be encoded as
four 1s followed by 0, et cetera.
So now, now you can imagine how
many bits do we have to use for
a large number like 100.
So, how many bits do I have to use for
exactly for a number like 100?
Well, exactly, we have to use 100 bits,
but so, it's the same number of
bits as the value of this number.
So, this is very inefficient.
If you were likely to
see some large numbers,
imagine if you occasionally see a number
like 1000, you have to use 1000 bits.
So, this only works where if you
are absolutely sure that there would be no
large numbers.
Mostly very frequent,
they're often using very small numbers.
Now, how do you decode this code?
Since these are variables
lengths in coding methods, and
you can't just count how many bits and
then just stop.
Right?
You can say eight bits or 32 bits,
then you, you will start another code.
There are variable lengths, so,
you have to rely on some mechanism.
In this case for unary, you can see
it's very easy to see the boundary.
Now you can easily see 0 would
signal the end of encoding.
So you just count how many 1s you
have seen, and then you hit the 0.
You know you have finished one number,
you start another number.
Now which is to start at unary code is to
aggressive in rewarding small numbers.
And if you occasionally can see a very
big number, it will be a disaster.
So what about some other
less aggressive method?
Well, gamma coding is one of them.
And in this method, we can do,
use unary coding for
a transformed form of the value.
So it's 1 plus the flow of log of x.
So the magnitude of this value is
much lower than the original, x.
So that's why we have four
using urinary code for that so,
and so we, first we have the urinary
code for coding this log of s.
And this will be followed by
a uniform code or binary code, and
this is basically the same uniform
code and binary code are the same.
And we're going to use this code to code
the remaining part of the value of x.
And this is basically, precisely,
x minus 1, 2 to the flow of log of x.
So the unary code or basically code
with a flow of log of x, well,
I added one there, and here.
But the remaining part will,
we using uniform
code to actually code
the difference between the x and
and this, 2 to the log of x.
And, and it's easy to to show that for
this this value, there's difference.
We only need to use up to,
this many bits and
in flow of log of x bits.
And this is easy to understand,
if the difference is too large then we
would have a higher flow of log of x.
So, here are some examples.
For example, 3 is encoded as 101.
The first two digits are the unary code.
Right.
So, this is for the value 2.
10 encodes 2 in unary coding.
And so, that means log of x,
the flow of log of x is 1,
because we will actually use unary code
to encode 1 plus the flow of log of x.
Since this is 2, then we know that
the floor of log of x is actually 1.
So but,
3 is still larger than 2 to the 1, so
the difference is 1, and
that 1 is encoded here at the end.
So that's why we have 101 for 3.
Now, similarly 5 is encoded
as 110 followed by 01.
And in this case,
the unary code encodes 3.
So, this is the unary code for 110 and
so the floor of log of x is 2.
And that means, we will compute
the difference between 5 and
the 2 to the 2, and that's 1, and
so we now have again 1 at the end.
But this time, we're going to
use two bits because with this
level of flow of log of x,
we could have more numbers, 5, 6, 7.
They would all share the same prefix here,
110.
So, in order to differentiate them,
we have to use two bits,
in the end to differentiate them.
So you can imagine 6 would be, 10 here
in the end instead of 01, after 110.
It's also true that the form
of a gamma code is always,
the first odd number of bits,
and in the center, there was a 0.
That's the end of the unary code.
And before that, or to, on the left
side of this 0, there will be all 1s.
And on the right side of this 0,
it's binary coding or uniform coding.
So how can you decode such a code?
Well, you again first do unary coding,
right?
Once you hit 0,
you know you have got the unary code.
And this also will tell you how many
bits you have to read further to
decode the uniform code.
So this is how you can
decode a gamma code.
There is also delta code, but
that's basically same as gamma code,
except that you replace the unary
prefix with the gamma code.
So that's even less
conservative than gamma code,
in terms of avoiding the small integers.
So that means it's okay if you
occasionally see a large number.
It's, it's, you know,
it's okay with delta code.
It's also fine with gamma code.
It's really a big loss for unary code,
and they are all operating,
of course, at different degrees of
favoring short favoring small integers.
And that also means they would
appropriate for sorting distribution.
But none of them is perfect for
all distributions.
And which method works,
the best would have to depend on
the actual distribution in your data set.
For inverted index, compression,
people have found that gamma
coding seems to work well.
So how to uncompress inverted index?
We just, talked about this.
Firstly, you decode those encode integers.
And we just, I think discussed how we
decode unary coding and gamma coding.
So I won't repeat.
What about the document IDs that
might be compressed using d-gap?
Well, we're going to do
sequential decoding.
So suppose the encoded idealist is x1,
x2, x3 et cetera.
We first decode x1 to obtain
the first document ID, ID1.
Then, we will decode x2,
which is actually the difference between
the second ID and the first one.
So we have to add the decoded value
of x2 to ID1 to recover the value
of the,
the ID at this secondary position, right.
So this is where you can see the advantage
of, converting document IDs into integers.
And that allows us to do this
kind of compression, and
we just repeat until we
decode all the documents.
Every time we use the document
ID in the previous position
to help recover the document
ID in the next position.
[MUSIC]