[SOUND]
So let's plug in these model masses
into the ranking function to
see what we will get, okay?
This is a general smoothing.
So a general ranking function for
smoothing with subtraction and
you have seen this before.
And now we have a very specific smoothing
method, the JM smoothing method.
So now let's see what what's a value for
office of D here.
And what's the value for p sub c here?
Right, so we may need to decide this
in order to figure out the exact
form of the ranking function.
And we also need to figure
out of course alpha.
So let's see.
Well this ratio is basically this,
right, so,
here, this is the probability
of c board on the top,
and this is the probability
of unseen war or,
in other words basically 11
times basically the alpha here,
this, so it's easy to see that.
This can be then rewritten as this.
Very simple.
So we can plug this into here.
And then here, what's the value for alpha?
What do you think?
So it would be just lambda, right?
And what would happen if we plug in
this value here, if this is lambda.
What can we say about this?
Does it depend on the document?
No, so it can be ignored.
Right?
So we'll end up having this
ranking function shown here.
And in this case you can easy to see,
this a precisely a vector space
model because this part is
a sum over all the matched query terms,
this is an element of the query map.
What do you think is a element
of the document up there?
Well it's this, right.
So that's our document left element.
And let's further examine what's
inside of this logarithm.
Well one plus this.
So it's going to be nonnegative,
this log of this,
it's going to be at least 1, right?
And these, this is a parameter,
so lambda is parameter.
And let's look at this.
Now this is a TF.
Now we see very clearly
this TF weighting here.
And the larger the count is,
the higher the weighting will be.
We also see IDF weighting,
which is given by this.
And we see docking the lan's
relationship here.
So all these heuristics
are captured in this formula.
What's interesting that
we kind of have got this
weighting function automatically
by making various assumptions.
Whereas in the vector space model,
we had to go through those heuristic
design in order to get this.
And in this case note that
there's a specific form.
And when you see whether this
form actually makes sense.
All right so what do you think
is the denominator here, hm?
This is a math of document.
Total number of words,
multiplied by the probability of the word
given by the collection, right?
So this actually can be interpreted
as expected account over word.
If we're going to draw, a word,
from the connection that we model.
And, we're going to draw as many as
the number of words in the document.
If you do that,
the expected account of a word, w,
would be precisely given
by this denominator.
So, this ratio basically,
is comparing the actual count, here.
The actual count of the word in the
document with expected count given by this
product if the word is in fact following
the distribution in the clutch this.
And if this counter is larger than
the expected counter in this part,
this ratio would be larger than one.
So that's actually a very
interesting interpretation, right?
It's very natural and intuitive,
it makes a lot of sense.
And this is one advantage of using
this kind of probabilistic reasoning
where we have made explicit assumptions.
And, we know precisely why
we have a logarithm here.
And, why we have these probabilities here.
And, we also have a formula that
intuitively makes a lot of sense and
does TF-IDF weighting and
documenting and some others.
Let's look at the,
the Dirichlet Prior Smoothing.
It's very similar to
the case of JM smoothing.
In this case,
the smoothing parameter is mu and
that's different from
lambda that we saw before.
But the format looks very similar.
The form of the function
looks very similar.
So we still have linear operation here.
And when we compute this ratio,
one will find that is that
the ratio is equal to this.
And what's interesting here is that we
are doing another comparison here now.
We're comparing the actual count.
Which is the expected account of the world
if we sampled meal worlds according to
the collection world probability.
So note that it's interesting we don't
even see docking the lens here and
lighter in the JMs model.
All right so this of course
should be plugged into this part.
So you might wonder, so
where is docking lens.
Interestingly the docking lens
is here in alpha sub d so
this would be plugged into this part.
As a result what we get is
the following function here and
this is again a sum over
all the match query words.
And we're against the queer,
the query, time frequency here.
And you can interpret this as
the element of a document vector,
but this is no longer
a single dot product, right?
Because we have this part,
I know that n is the name of the query,
right?
So that just means if
we score this function,
we have to take a sum over
all the query words, and
then do some adjustment of
the score based on the document.
But it's still, it's still clear
that it does documents lens
modulation because this lens
is in the denominator so
a longer document will
have a lower weight here.
And we can also see it has tf here and
now idf.
Only that this time the form of the
formula is different from the previous one
in JMs one.
But intuitively it still implements TFIDF
waiting and document lens rendition again,
the form of the function is dictated
by the probabilistic reasoning and
assumptions that we have made.
Now there are also
disadvantages of this approach.
And that is, there's no guarantee
that there's such a form
of the formula will actually work well.
So if we look about at this geo function,
all those TF-IDF waiting and document lens
rendition for example it's unclear whether
we have sub-linear transformation.
Unfortunately we can see here there
is a logarithm function here.
So we do have also the,
so it's here right?
So we do have the sublinear
transformation, but
we do not intentionally do that.
That means there's no guarantee that
we will end up in this, in this way.
Suppose we don't have logarithm,
then there's no sub-linear transformation.
As we discussed before, perhaps
the formula is not going to work so well.
So that's an example of the gap
between a formal model like this and
the relevance that we have to model,
which is really a subject
motion that is tied to users.
So it doesn't mean we cannot fix this.
For example, imagine if we did
not have this logarithm, right?
So we can take a risk and
we're going to add one,
or we can even add double logarithm.
But then, it would mean that the function
is no longer a proper risk model.
So the consequence of
the modification is no
longer as predictable as
what we have been doing now.
So, that's also why, for example,
PM45 remains very competitive and
still, open channel how to use
public risk models as they arrive,
better model than the PM25.
In particular how do we use query
like how to derive a model and
that would work consistently
better than DM 25.
Currently we still cannot do that.
Still interesting open question.
So to summarize this part, we've talked
about the two smoothing methods.
Jelinek-Mercer which is doing the fixed
coefficient linear interpolation.
Dirichlet Prior this is what add a pseudo
counts to every word and is doing adaptive
interpolation in that the coefficient
would be larger for shorter documents.
In most cases we can see, by using these
smoothing methods, we will be able to
reach a retrieval function where
the assumptions are clearly articulate.
So they are less heuristic.
Explaining the results also show
that these, retrieval functions.
Also are very effective and they are
comparable to BM 25 or pm lens adultation.
So this is a major advantage
of probably smaller
where we don't have to do
a lot of heuristic design.
Yet in the end that we naturally
implemented TF-IDF weighting and
doc length normalization.
Each of these functions also has
precise ones smoothing parameter.
In this case of course we still need
to set this smoothing parameter.
There are also methods that can be
used to estimate these parameters.
So overall,
this shows by using a probabilistic model,
we follow very different strategies
then the vector space model.
Yet, in the end, we end up uh,with
some retrievable functions that
look very similar to
the vector space model.
With some advantages in having
assumptions clearly stated.
And then, the form dictated
by a probabilistic model.
Now, this also concludes our discussion of
the query likelihood probabilistic model.
And let's recall what
assumptions we have made
in order to derive the functions
that we have seen in this lecture.
Well we basically have made four
assumptions that I listed here.
The first assumption is that the relevance
can be modeled by the query likelihood.
And the second assumption with med is, are
query words are generated independently
that allows us to decompose
the probability of the whole query
into a product of probabilities
of old words in the query.
And then,
the third assumption that we have made is,
if a word is not seen,
the document or in the late,
its probability proportional to
its probability in the collection.
That's a smoothing with
a collection ama model.
And finally, we made one of these
two assumptions about the smoothing.
So we either used JM smoothing or
Dirichlet prior smoothing.
If we make these four assumptions
then we have no choice but
to take the form of the retrieval
function that we have seen earlier.
Fortunately the function has a nice
property in that it implements TF-IDF
weighting and document machine and
these functions also work very well.
So in that sense,
these functions are less heuristic
compared with the vector space model.
And there are many extensions of this,
this basic model and
you can find the discussion of them in
the reference at the end of this lecture.
[MUSIC]