[SOUND] This lecture is about
the probabilistic retrieval model.
In this lecture, we're going to continue
the discussion of text retrieval methods.
We're going to look at another kind of
very different way to design ranking
functions, then the Vector Space Model
that we discussed before.
In probabilistic models we define
the ranking function based
on the probability that this
document is random to this query.
In other words, we are, we introduced
a binary random variable here.
This is the variable R here.
And we also assume that the query and
the documents are all observations
from random variables.
Note that in the vector space model,
we assume they are vectors.
But here we assumed we assumed they are
the data observed from random variables.
And so the problem, model retrieval
becomes to estimate
the probability of relevance.
In this category of models,
there are different variants.
The classic probabilistic model has
led to the BM25 retrieval function,
which we discussed in
the vector space model,
because it's form is actually
similar to a vector space model.
In this lecture,
we're going to discuss another subclass in
this big class called a language
modeling approaches to retrieval.
In particular, we're going to discuss
the Query Likelihood retrieval model,
which is one of the most effective
models in probabilistic models.
There is also another line called
a divergence-from-randomness model,
which has latitude the PL2 function.
It's also one of the most effective
state of the art attribute functions.
In query likelihood, our assumption
is that this probability readiness
can be approximated by the probability
of query given a document and readiness.
So, intuitively, this probability just
captures the following probability.
And that is if a user likes document d,
how likely would
the user enter query q in
order to retrieve document d.
So we'll assume that the user likes d,
because we have a relevance value here.
And the we ask the question about
how likely we will see this
particular query from this user?
So this is the basic idea.
Now to understand this idea,
let's take a look at the general idea or
the basic idea of probabilistic
retrieval models.
So here, I listed some imagined
relevance status values or
relevance judgments of queries and
documents.
For example, in this slide,
it shows that query one
is a query that the user typed in and
d1 is a document the user has seen and
one means the user thinks
d1 is relevant to to q1.
So this R here can be also approximated
by the clicks little data that the search
engine can collect it by watching how
you interact with the search results.
So, in this case, let's say,
the user clicked on this document, so
there's a one here.
Similarly, the user clicked on d2 also,
so there's a one here.
In other words,
d2 is assumed to relevant at two, q1.
On the other hand, d3 is non relevant,
there's a zero here.
And d4 is non-relevant and then d 5 is
again relevant and so on and so forth.
And this part of maybe,
they are collected from a different user.
Right.
So this user typed in q1 and
then found that d1 is actually not useful,
so d1 is actually non-relevant.
In contrast here we see it's relevant and,
or this could be the same query typing
by the same user at different times,
but d2 is also relevant, et cetera.
And then here, we can see more
data that about other queries.
Now we can imagine,
we have a lot of search data.
Now we can ask the question,
how can we then estimated
the probability of relevance?
Right.
So
how can we compute this
probability of relevance?
Well, intuitively,
that just means if we look at the,
all the entries where we see this
particular d and this particular q,
how likely will we see
a one on the third column?
Basically, that just means
we can correct the counts.
We can first count how many
times where we see q and
d as a pair in this table and
then count how many times
we actually have also seen
one in the third column and
then we just compute the ratio.
So let's take a look at
some specific examples.
Suppose we are trying to computed this
probability for d1, d2 and d3 for q1.
What is the estimated probability?
Now think about that.
You can pause the video if needed.
Try to take a look at the table and
try to give your estimate
of the probability.
Have you seen that if we are interested
in q1 and d1, we've been looking at the,
these two pairs and in both cases or
actually in one of the cases,
the user has said that this is one,
this is relevant.
So R is equal to 1 in only
one of the two cases.
In the other case, this is zero.
So that's one out of two.
What about the d1 and the d2?
Well, they're are here,
you want d2, d1, d2.
In both cases,
in this case R is equal to 1.
So, it's two out of two and
so and so forth.
So you can see with this approach,
we captured it score these documents for
the query.
Right?
We now have a score for d1,
d2 and d3 for this query.
We can simply ranked them based
on these probabilities and so
that's the basic idea of
probabilistic retrieval model.
And you can see, it makes a lot of sense.
In this case, it's going to rank
d2 above all the other documents.
Because in all the cases, when you
have seen q1 and d2, R is equal to 1.
The user clicked on this document.
So this also showed showed that
with a lot of click through data,
a search engine can learn a lot from
the data to improve the search engine.
This is a simple example that shows that
with even a small number of entries here,
we can already estimate
some probabilities.
These probabilities would give us some
sense about which document might be more
read or more useful to a user for
typing this query.
Now, of course, the problem is that
we don't observe all the queries and
all of the documents and
all the relevance values.
Right?
There will be a lot of unseen documents.
In general, we can only collect data from
the document's that we have shown to
the users.
There are even more unseen queries,
because you cannot predict what
queries will be typed in by users.
So, obviously, this approach won't work
if we apply it to unseen queries or
unseen documents.
Nevertheless, this shows the basic idea
of the probabilistic retrieval model and
it makes sense intuitively.
So what do we do in such a case when we
have a lot of unseen documents and, and
unseen queries?
Well, the solutions that we have
to approximate in some way.
Right.
So, in this particular case called
the Query LIkelihood Retrieval Model,
we just approximate this
by another conditional probability,
p q | d, R is equal to 1.
So, in the condition part, we assume
that the user likes the document,
because we have seen that the user
clicked on this document.
And this part,
shows that we're interested in how likely
the user would actually enter this query.
How likely we will see this
query in the same row.
So note that here, we have made
an interesting assumption here.
Basically, we, we're going to assume
that whether the user types in this
query has something to do with
whether user likes the document.
In other words, we actually
make the foreign assumption and
that is a user formula to query based
on an imaginary relevant document.
Well, if you just look at this
as a conditional probability,
it's not obvious we
are making this assumption.
So what I really meant
is that to use this new
conditional probability to help us score
then this new condition of probability.
We have to somehow be able
to estimate this conditional
probability without
relying on this big table.
Otherwise, it would be having
similar problems as before.
And by making this assumption, we have
some way to bypass this big table and
try to just mortar how to
use a formula to the query.
Okay.
So this is how you can simplify the,
the general model so that we can
give either specific function later.
So let's look at how this model works for
our example.
And basically,
what we are going to do in this case
is to ask the following question.
Which of these documents is most likely
the imaginary relevant document in
the user's mind when the user
formulates this query?
And so we ask this question and
we quantify the probability and this
probability is a conditional probability
of observing this query if a particular
document is in fact the imaginary
relevant document in the user's mind.
Here you can see we compute all these
query likelihood probabilities,
the likelihood of queries
given each document.
Once we have these values,
we can then rank these documents
based on these values.
So to summarize, the general idea of
modern relevance in the probability
risk model is to assume that we introduce
a binary random variable, R here.
And then let the scoring function be
defined based on this conditional
probability.
We also talked about a proximate in this
[SOUND] by using the query likelihood.
And in this case,
we have a ranking function that's
basically based on a probability
of a query given the document.
And this probability should be
interpreted as the probability
that a user who likes document
d would pose query q.
Now the question, of course is how do
we compute this additional probability?
At this in general has to do with how
to compute the probability of text,
because q is a text.
And this has to do with a model
called a Language Model.
And this kind of models
are proposed to model text.
So most specifically, we will be
very interested in the following
conditional probability as I show you,
you this here.
If the user like this document, how
likely the user would approve this query?
And in the next lecture, we're going
to give introduction to Language Model,
so that we can see how we can model text
with a probability risk model in general.
[MUSIC]