[SOUND]
This lecture is about the specific
smoothing methods for language models
used in Probabilistic Retrieval Model.
In this lecture we will continue
the discussion of language models for
information retrieval, particularly
the query likelihood retrieval method.
And we're going to talk about
the specific smoothing methods used for
such a retrieval function.
So, this is a slide from a previous
lecture where we show that with
query likelihood ranking and the smoothing
with the collection language model.
We end up having a retrieval function
that looks like the following.
So, this is the retrieval function,
based on these assumptions
that we have discussed.
You can see it's a sum of all
the matched query terms here.
And inside the sum it's
a count of term in the query,
and some weight for
the term in the document.
We have TFI, TF weight here.
And then we have another constant here,
in n.
So clearly, if we want to implement this
function using a programming language,
we'll still need to figure
out a few variables.
In particular, we're going to
need to know how to estimate the,
probability of would exactly.
And how do we set alpha?
So in order to answer these questions,
we have to think about this very specific
smoothing methods, and
that is the main topic of this lecture.
We're going to talk about
two smoothing methods.
The first is the simple linear
interpolation, with a fixed coefficient.
And this is also called a Jelinek and
Mercer smoothing.
So the idea is actually very simple.
This picture shows how we estimate
document language model by using
maximum [INAUDIBLE] method,
that gives us word counts normalized by
the total number of words in the text.
The idea of using this method is to
maximize the probability
of the observed text.
As a result, if a word like network,
is not observed in the text.
It's going to get zero probability,
as shown here.
So the idea of smoothing, then,
is to rely on collection average model,
where this word is not going to have
a zero probability to help us decide
what non-zero probability should
be assigned to such a word.
So, we can know that network as
a non-zero probability here.
So, in this approach what we do is,
we do a linear interpolation between
the maximum likelihood or estimate here
and the collection language model.
And this controlled by
the smoothing parameter, lambda.
Which is between 0 and 1.
So this is a smoothing parameter.
The larger lambda is the two the more
smoothing we have, we will have.
So by mixing them together, we achieve the
goal of assigning non-zero probability.
And these two are word in our network.
So let's see how it works for
some of the words here.
For example if we compute to
the smallest probability for text.
Now, the next one right here
is made give us 10 over 100,
and that's going to be here.
But the connection probability is this, so
we just combine them together
with this simple formula.
We can also see a, the word network.
Which used to have zero probability
now is getting a non-zero
probability of this value.
And that's because the count is going
to be zero for network here, but
this part is non zero and
that's basically how this method works.
If you think about this and
you can easily see now the alpha sub d
in this smoothing method is basically
lambda because that's, remember,
the coefficient in front of
the probability of the word given by
the collection language model here, right?
Okay, so
this is the first smoothing method.
The second one is similar, but it has
a find end for manual interpretation.
It's often called a duration of the ply or
Bayesian smoothing.
So again here, we face the problem of
zero probability for like network.
Again we'll use the collection
language model, but
in this case we're going to combine
them in a somewhat different ways.
The formula first can be seen as
a interpolation of the maximum
and the collection
language model as before.
As in the J M's [INAUDIBLE].
Only and after the coefficient [INAUDIBLE]
is not the lambda, a fixed lambda, but
a dynamic coefficient in this form,
when mu is a parameter,
it's a non, negative value.
And you can see if we
set mu to a constant,
the effect is that a long document would
actually get smaller coefficient here.
Right?
Because a long document
we have a longer length.
Therefore, the coefficient
is actually smaller.
And so a long document would have
less smoothing as we would expect.
So this seems to make more sense
than a fixed coefficient smoothing.
Of course,
this part would be of this form, so
that the two coefficients would sum to 1.
Now, this is one way to understand
that this is smoothing.
Basically, it means that it's
a dynamic coefficient interpolation.
There is another way to
understand this formula.
Which is even easier to remember and
that's this side.
So it's easy to see we can rewrite
this modern method in this form.
Now, in this form, we can easily see
what change we have made to the maximum
estimator, which would be this part,
right?
So it normalizes the count
by the top elements.
So, in this form, we can see what we did,
is we add this to the count of every word.
So, what does this mean?
Well, this is basically
something relative to the probability
of the word in the collection..
And we multiply that by the parameter mu.
And when we combine this
with the count here,
essentially we are adding pseudo
counts to the observed text.
We pretend every word,
has got this many pseudocount.
So the total count would be
the sum of these pseudocount and
the actual count of
the word in the document.
As a result, in total, we would
have added this minute pseudocount.
Why?
Because if you take a sum of this,
this one, move over all the words and
we'll see the probability of the words
would sum to 1, and that gives us just mu.
So this is the total number of
pseudo counters that we added.
And, and so
these probabilities would still sum to 1.
So in this case, we can easily
see the method is essentially to
add these as a pseudocount to this data.
Pretend we actually augment the data
by including by some pseudo data defined
by the collection language model.
As a result, we have more counts.
It's the, the total counts for, for
word, a word that would be like this.
And, as a result,
even if a word has zero counts here.
And say if we have zero come here and
that it would still have none,
zero count because of this part, right?
And so this is how this method works.
Let's also take a look at
this specific example here.
All right, so for text again,
we will have 10 as original count.
That we actually observe but
we also added some pseudocount.
And so, the probability of
text would be of this form.
Naturally the probability of
network would be just this part.
And so, here you can also
see what's alpha sub d here.
Can you see it?
If you want to think about
you can pause the video.
Have you noticed that this
part is basically of a sub t?
So we can see this case of our sub t
does depend on the document, right?
Because this lens depends on the document
whereas in the linear interpolation.
The James move method
this is the constant.
[MUSIC]