This lecture is about query likelihood and
probabilistic retrieval model.
In this lecture,
we continue the discussion of
probabilistic retrieval model.
In particular,
we're going to talk about the query
likelihood of the retrieval function.
In the query of likelihood retrieval
model our idea is a model.
How a likely a user, who likes a document
would pose a particular query.
So in this case, you can imagine,
if a user likes this particular document
about the presidential campaign news.
Then we can assume,
the user would use this
working as a basis to oppose a query
to try and retrieve this doc.
So you can imagine the user, could use
a process that works as follows, where
we assume that the query is generated
by sampling words from the document.
So for example,
a user might pick a word like
presidential from this document,
and then use this as a query word.
And then the user would pick another word,
like campaign and
that would be the second query word.
Now this, of course,
is assumption that we have made about,
how a user would post a query.
Whether a user actually
followed this process.
Maybe a different question.
But this assumption,
has allowed us to formally characterize
this conditional probability.
And this allows to also not rely on
the big table that I showed you earlier
to use imperative data to
estimate this probability.
And this is why we can use this
idea to then further derive
retrieval function that we can
implement with the languages.
So, as you see, the assumption that
we've made here is, each query word,
is independent in this sample, and also,
each word is basically
obtained from the document.
So now let's see how this works exactly.
Well, since we are computing
a query likelihood,
then the probability here is just
the probability of this particular query,
which is a sequence of words.
And we make the assumption that each
word is generated independently.
So, as a result, the probability
of the query is just a product
of the probability of each query word.
Now, how do we compute
the probability of each query word?
Well, based on the assumption,
that a word is picked from the document,
that the user has in mind.
Now we know the probability
of each word is just the,
the relative frequency of
the word in the document.
So, for example the probability of
presidential given the document,
would be just the count of
presidential in the document,
divided by the total number of words
in the document or document length.
So with this these assumptions,
we now have actual simple formula for
retrieval, right?
We can use this to rank our document.
So does this model work?
Let's take a look, here are some example
documents that you have seen before.
Suppose now the query is
presidential campaign.
And we see the formula here on the top.
So how do we score these documents?
Well it's very simple, right,
we just count how many times we have seen
presidential, how many times
we have seen campaign etc.
And see here 44 and
we've seen president Jou Tai,
so that's two over the lands
of document the four.
Multiply by 1 over lands of document
of 4 for the probability of
campaign and seeming we can probabilities
for the other two documents.
Now if you'll look at this, these numbers
or these, this, these formulas for
scoring all these documents, it seems to
make sense because, if we assume d3 and
d4 have about the same length,
then it looks like we will rank d4
above d3 and which is above d2, right?
And as we would expect, looks like
it did capture the tf heuristic.
And so this seems to work well.
However, if we try a different
query like this one,
presidential campaign update,
then we might see a problem.
But what problem?
Well, think about update, now none of
these documents has mentioned update.
So according to our assumption that
a user would pick a order from a document
to generate a query,
then the probability of obtaining
a word like update would be what.
Would be zero, right?
So that cause a problem,
because it would cause all these documents
to have zero probability
of generating this query.
Now, while it's fine to have a zero
probability for d2 which is not relevant.
It's not okay to have zero for d3 and
d4, because now we no longer
can distinguish them.
What's worse,
we can't even distinguish them from d 2.
All right, so
that's obviously not desirable.
Now when one has such result, we should
think about what has caused this problem.
So we have to examine what
assumptions have been made,
as we derive this ranking function.
Now if you examine those assumptions
carefully you would realize.
What has caused this problem, right?
So, take a moment to think about,
what do you think is the reason why
update has zero probability,
and how do we fix it?
Right?
So, if you think about this for
the moment that you realize that.
That's because we have made an assumption
that every query word must be drawn
from the document in the user's mind.
So, in order to fix this,
we have to assume that,
the user could have drawn a word,
not necessarily from the document.
So let's see improved model.
An improvement here is to say that,
well, instead of drawing a word from
the document, let's imagine that the user
would actually draw a word from a document
model and so I show a model here.
Here we assume that this
document is generated,
by using this unigram image model.
Now, this model, doesn't necessarily
assign zero probability for update.
In fact we assume this model does not
assign zero probability for any word.
Now if we're thinking this
way then the generation
process is a little bit different.
Now the user has this model in mind,
instead of this particular document.
Although the model has to be
estimated based on the document.
So the user can again generate
the query using a similar process.
They may pick a word, for example
presidential and another word campaign.
Now the difference is that, this time
we can also pick a word like update,
even though update it
doesn't occur in the document
to potentially generate
a query word like update.
So that, a query was updated we
want to have zero probabilities.
So this would fix our problem and
it's also reasonable,
because we're now thinking of what the
user is looking for in a more general way,
that is unique language model
instead of a fixed document.
So how do we compute this query,
like if we make this sum where
it involves two steps, right?
The first is the computer's model, and we
call it talking the language model here.
For example, I have shown two
possible energy models here.
This has been based on two documents.
And then given a query and
I get a mining algorithms.
The second step, is just to compute
the likelihood of this query.
And by making independence assumptions,
we could then have this probability as
a product of the probability
of each query word, all right?
But we do this for both documents.
And then we're going to score these
two documents and then rank them.
So that's the basic idea of this
query likelihood retrieval function.
So more generally than this ranking
function would look like the following and
here as, we assume that query
has end words W1 through WN.
And then the scoring function,
the ranking function is the probability
that we observe this query, given that
the user is thinking of this document.
And this assumed to be product of
probabilities of all individual words and
this is based on
the independence assumption.
Now we actually often score the,
document for
this query by using log of the query
likelihood, as shown on the sigma line.
Now we do this to avoid having
a lot of small probabilities.
M, multiplied together.
And this could cause underflow and
we might lose precision by transforming
the value as a logarithm function.
We maintain the order of these documents,
yet we can avoid the end of flow problem.
So if we take longer than transformation
of coarse the product that would become
a sum, as you stake in the line here.
So it's a sum of all of the query words,
and inside the sum
that is log of the probability of
this word given by the document.
And then we can further rewrite the sum,
into a different form.
So in the first of the sum here,
in this sum,
we have it over all the query
words n query words.
And in this sum, we have a sum
of all the possible words but
we put a counter here of
each word in the query.
Essentially we are only considering
the words in the query,
because if a word is not in the query,
it can would be zero.
So we're still considering
only these end words.
But we're using a different form as if
we were going to a sum of all the words,
in the vocabulary.
And of course a word might occur
multiple times in the query.
That's wh, why we have a count here.
And then this part is
log of the probability of the word
given by the document MG model.
So you can see, in this material function,
we actually know the count
of the word in the query.
So, the only thing that we don't know
is this document language model.
Therefore, we can convert
through the retrieval problem
into the problem of estimating
this document language model.
So that we can compute, the probability of
each query we're given by this document.
At different estimation methods here,
would lead to different ranking functions.
And this is just like a different
a ways to place a doc in the vector,
in the vector space.
Would lead it to a different ranking
function in the vector space model.
Here are different ways to estimate
this stuff in the language model,
will lead you to a different ranking
function for query likelihood.
[MUSIC]