[SOUND]
So, I showed you how we rewrite the into
a form that looks like a,
the formula on this slide.
After we make the assumption about
smoothing the language model
based on the collection
of the language model.
Now, if we look at the, this rewriting,
it actually would give us two benefits.
The first benefit is, it helps us better
understand that this ranking function.
In particular, we're going to show that
from this formula we can see smoothing is
the correction that we model will give
us something like a TF-IDF weighting and
length normalization.
The second benefit is
that it also allows us to
compute the query likelihood
more efficiently.
In particular,
we see that the main part of the formula
is a sum over the matching query terms.
So, this is much better than if we
take the sum over all the words.
After we smooth the document
the language model,
we essentially have nonzero
probabilities for all the words.
So, this new form of the formula is
much easier to score, or to compute.
It's also interesting to note
that the last of term here
is actually independent of the document.
Since our goal is to
rank the documents for
the same query,
we can ignore this term for ranking.
Because it's going to be the same for
all the documents.
Ignoring it wouldn't effect
the order of the documents.
Inside the sum,
we also see that each matched
query term would contribute a weight.
And this weight actually,
is very interesting because it
looks like TF-IDF weighting.
First, we can already see it has
a frequency of the word in the query,
just like in the vector space model.
When we take adult product,
we see the word frequency in
the query to show up in such a sum.
And so naturally,
this part will correspond to
the vector element from
the document vector.
And here, indeed, we can see it actually
encodes a weight that has similar
factor to TF-IDF weighting.
I let you examine it.
Can you see it?
Can you see which part is capturing TF,
and which part is capturing IDF weighting?
So if you want, you can pause
the video to think more about it.
So, have you noticed that this p sub-seen
is related to the term frequency
in the sense that if a word occurs
very frequently in the document,
then the S probability here
will tend to be larger.
Right?
So, this means this term is really
doing something like TF weighting.
Have you also noticed that
this time in the denominator
is actually achieving the factor of IDF?
Why?
Because this is the popularity of the term
in the collection, but
it's in the denominator.
So, if the probability in
the collection is larger
than the weight is actually smaller.
And, this means a popular term.
We actually have a smaller weight.
And, this is precisely what
IDF weighting is doing.
Only not, we now have
a different form of TF and IDF.
Remember, IDF has a log,
logarithm of document frequency, but
here we have something different.
But intuitively,
it achieves a similar effect.
Interestingly, we also have something
related to the length normalization.
Again, can you see which factor is
related to the length in this formula.
Well, I just say that, that this
term is related to IDF weighting.
This, this collection probability.
But, it turns out this term here
is actually related to
a document length normalization.
In particular,
D might be related to document N, length.
So, it, it encodes how much probability
mass we want to give to unseen words.
How much smoothing you are allowed to do.
Intuitively, if a document is long,
then we need to do less smoothing.
Because we can assume that
it is large enough that,
we have probably observed all of the words
that the author could have written.
But if the document is short,
the unseen are expected to be to be large,
and we need to do more smoothing.
It's like that there are words that have
not been retained yet by the author.
So, this term appears to
paralyze long documents
tend to be longer than,
larger than for long document.
But note that the also occurs here.
And so,
this may not actually be necessary,
penalizing long documents, and
in fact is not so clear here.
But as we will see later, when we
consider some specific smoothing methods,
it turns out that they do
penalize long documents.
Just like in TF-IDF weighting and
the document ends formulas
in the vector space model.
So, that's a very interesting
observation because it means
we don't even have to think about
the specific way of doing smoothing.
We just need to assume that if we
smooth with this language model,
then we would have a formula that
looks like a TF-IDF weighting and
document length normalization.
What's also interesting that we have
a very fixed form of the ranking function.
And see, we have not heuristically
put a logarithm here.
In fact, if you can think about,
why we would have a logarithm here?
If you look at the assumptions that
we have made, it will be clear.
It's because we have used a logarithm
of query likelihood for scoring.
And, we turned the product into
a sum of logarithm of probability.
And, that's why we have this logarithm.
Note that if we only want to heuristically
implement a TF weighting and
IDF weighting, we don't necessarily
have to have a logarithm here.
Imagine if we drop this logarithm,
we would still have TF and IDF weighting.
But, what's nice with
probabilistic modeling is that we
are automatically given
a logarithm function here.
And, that's basically,
a fixed reform of the formula that we did
not really have to hueristically line.
And in this case,
if you try to drop this logarithm
the model probably won't, won't work
as well as if you keep the logarithm.
So, a nice property of probabilistic
modeling is that by following some
assumptions and the probability rules,
we'll get a formula automatically.
And, the formula would have
a particular form, like in this case.
And, if we hueristically
design the formula,
we may not necessarily end up
having such a specific form.
So to summarize, we talked about the need
for smoothing a document and model.
Otherwise, it would give zero probability
for unseen words in the document.
And, that's not good for
scoring a query with such an unseen word.
It's also necessary,
in general, to improve the acc,
accuracy of estimating the model
representing the topic of this document.
The general idea of smoothing in retrieval
is to use the connection language model
to give us some clue about which unseen
word would have a higher probability.
That is the probability of the unseen
word is assumed to be proportional
to its probability in the collection.
With this assumption, we've shown that we
can derive a general ranking formula for
query likelihood.
That has a fact of TF-IDF waiting and
document length normalization.
We also see that through some rewriting,
the scoring of such ranking function,
is primarily based on sum of
weights on matched query terms,
just like in the vector space model.
But, the actual ranking function
is given us automatically by
the probability rules and
assumptions we have made.
Unlike in the vector space model,
where we have to heuristically think
about the form of the function.
However, we still need
to address the question,
how exactly we should we should
smooth a document image model?
How exactly we should use
the reference language model based on
the connection to adjusting
the probability of the maximum.
And, this is the topic
of the next to that.
[MUSIC]