This lecture is about
smoothing of language models.
In this lecture we're going to continue
talking about the probabilistic
retrieval model.
In particular, we're going to talk
about smoothing of language model and
the query likelihood of it,
which will method.
So you have seen this slide
from a previous lecture.
This is the ranking function
based on the query likelihood.
Here we assume that the independence
of generating each query word
and the formula would
look like the following.
Where we take a sum over all of the query
words and inside is the sum there is
a log of probability of a word given by
the document, or document language model.
So the main task now is to estimate
this document language model.
As we said before different methods for
estimating this model would lead
to different retrieval functions.
So, in this lecture we're going
to look into this in more detail.
So, how do I estimate this language model?
Well, the obvious choice would be
the Maximum Likelihood Estimate
that we have seen before.
And that is we're going to normalize
the word frequencies in the document.
And the estimated probability
would look like this.
This is a step function here.
Which means all the words
that have the same frequency
count will have an equal probability.
This is another frequency in the count
that has a different probability.
Note that for words that have not
occurred in the document here,
they all have zero probability.
So we know this is just like a model that
we assume earlier in the lecture, where
we assume the user with the sample word
from the document to formulate the query.
And there is no chance of sampling
any word that is not in the document.
And we know that's not good.
So how would we improve this?
Well, in order to assign
a non-zero probability
to words that have not been observed
in the document, we would have to take
away some probability to mass from
the words that are observing the document.
So for example here, we have to
take away some [INAUDIBLE] mass,
because we need some extra problem
in the mass for the unseen words.
Otherwise, they won't sum to 1.
So all these probabilities
must be sum to 1.
So to make this transformation, and
to improve the maximum [INAUDIBLE].
By assigning nonzero probabilities to
words that are not observed in the data.
We have to do smoothing, and smoothing
has to do with improving the estimate
by considering the possibility that,
if the author had been written.
Helping, asking to write more words for
the document.
The user,
the author might have rethink other words.
If you think about this factor
then a smoothed LM model
would be a more accurate
representation of the actual topic.
Imagine you have seen
abstract of such article.
Let's say this document is abstract.
Right.
If we assume and
see words in this abstract we have or,
or probability of 0 that
would mean it's no chance
of sampling a word outside the abstract
that the formula to query.
But imagine the user who is interested in
the topic of this abstract, the user might
actually choose a word that is not in
the abstractor to to use as query.
So obviously if we had asked
this author to write more,
the author would have written
a full text of that article.
So smoothing of the language
model is attempted to
to try to recover the model for
the whole, whole article.
And then of course we don't have written
knowledge about any words are not observed
in the abstract there, so that's why
smoothing is actually a tricky problem.
So let's talk a little more
about how to smooth a LM word.
The key question here is what probability
should be assigned to those unseen words.
Right.
And
there are many different
ways of doing that.
One idea here, that's very useful for
retrieval is let the probability
of an unseen word be proportional
to its probability given by
a reference language model.
That means if you don't observe
the word in the data set,
we're going to assume that
its probability is kind of
governed by another reference language
model that we were constructing.
It will tell us which unseen words
we have likely a higher probability.
In the case of retrieval
a natural choice would be to
take the Collection Language Model
as a Reference Language Model.
That is to say if you don't
observe a word in the document
we're going to assume that.
The probability of this word
would be proportional to the probability
of the word in the whole collection.
So, more formally,
we'll be estimating the probability of
a word getting a document as follows.
If the word is seen in the document,
then the probability
would be a discounted the maximum
[INAUDIBLE] estimated p sub c here.
Otherwise, if the word is not seen
in the document, we'll then let
probability be proportional to the
probability of the word in the collection,
and here the coefficient of is to
control the amount of probability
mass that we assign to unseen words.
Obviously all these
probabilities must sum to 1.
So, alpha sub d is
constrained in some way.
So, what if we plug in this
smoothing formula into our
query likelihood Ranking Function?
This is what we would get.
In this formula,
you can see, right, we have
this as a sum over all the query words.
And note that we have written in the form
of a sum over all the vocabulary.
You see here this is a sum of
all the words in the vocabulary,
but note that we have a count
of the word in the query.
So, in effect we are just taking
a sum of query words, right.
This is in now a common way that
we will use because of its
convenience in some transformations.
So, this is as I said,
this is sum of all the query words.
In our smoothing method,
we're assuming the words that are not
observed in the document, that we have
a somewhat different form of probability.
And then it's for this form.
So we're going to then decompose
this sum into two parts.
One sum is over all the query words
that are matched in the document.
That means in this sum,
all the words have a non
zero probability, in the document, sorry.
It's, the non zero count of
the word in the document.
They all occur in the document.
And they also have to, of course,
have a non-zero count in the query.
So, these are the words that are matched.
These are the query words that
are matched in the document.
On the other hand in this sum we are s,
taking the sum over all the words that
are note our query was not
matched in the document.
So they occur in the query due to this
term but they don't occur in the document.
In this case,
these words have this probability because
of our assumption about the smoothing.
But that here, these c words
have a different probability.
Now we can go further by
rewriting the second sum
as a difference of two other sums.
Basically the first sum is actually
the sum over all the query words.
Now we know that the original
sum is not over the query words.
This is over all the query words that
are not matched in the document.
So here we pretend that they
are actually over all the query words.
So, we take a sum over
all the query words.
Obviously this sum has
extra terms that are,
this sum has extra terms
that are not in this sum.
Because here we're taking sum
over all the query words.
There it's not matched in the document.
So in order to make them equal,
we have to then subtract another sum here.
And this is a sum over all the query
words that are mentioned in the document.
And this makes sense because here
we're considering all query words.
And then we subtract the query
that was matched in the document.
That will give us the query rules
that not matched in the document.
And this is almost a reverse
process of the first step here.
And you might wonder
why we want to do that.
Well, that's because if we do this then
we'll have different forms
of terms inside these sums.
So, now we can see in the sum we have,
all the words,
matched query words, matched in
the document with this kind of terms.
Here we have another sum
over the same set of terms.
Matched query terms in document.
But inside the sum it's different.
But these two sums can clearly be merged.
So, if we do that we'll get another form
of the formula that looks like
the following at the bottom here.
And note that this is a very interesting,
because here we combine the, these two,
that are a sum of the query words matched
in the document in the one sum here.
And the other sum, now is the compose
[INAUDIBLE] to two parts, and,
and these two parts look much simpler.
Just because these
are the probabilities of unseen words.
But this formula is very interesting,
because you can see the sum is now over
all the matched query terms.
And just like in the vector space model,
we take a sum of terms,
that intersection of query vector and
the document vector.
So it all already looks a little
bit like the vector space model.
In fact there is even more severity here.
As we, we explain on this slide.
[MUSIC]