[SOUND] This lecture is about
the feedback in the vector space model.
In this lecture, we continue talking
about the feedback and text retrieval.
Particularly we're going to talk about
feedback in the vector space model.
As we have discussed before in
the case of feedback the task of
a text retrieval system is relearned from
examples to improve retrieval accuracy.
We will have positive examples,
those are the documents that
are assumed that will be random or
judged with being random and all
the documents that are viewed by users.
We also have negative examples, those
are documents known to be non-relevant.
They can also be the documents
that are escaped by users.
The general method in
the vector space model for
feedback is to modify our query vector.
Now we want to place the query vector in
a better position to make that accurate
and what does that mean exactly?
Well, if you think about the query vector
that would mean you would have to do
something to vector elements.
And in general that would
mean we might add new terms.
We might adjust weights of old terms or
assign weights to new terms.
And as a result in general
the query will have more terms so
we often call this query expansion.
The most effective method in the vector
space model of feedback is called Rocchio
feedback which was actually
proposed several decades ago.
So, the idea is quite simple we illustrate
this idea by using a two-dimensional
display of all the documents in
the collection and also the query vector.
So, now we can see
the query vector is here in
the center and
these are all of the documents.
So when we use a query vector and
use a similarity function to
find the most similar documents.
We are basically drawing a circle here and
then these documents would be
basically the top-ranked documents.
And this process of relevant documents,
right?
And these are random documents for
example that's relevant, etc.
And then these minuses
are negative documents like this.
So our goal here is trying
to move this query vector to some position
to improve the retrieval accuracy.
By looking at this diagram
what do you think where
should we move the query vector so that
we can improve the retrieval accuracy.
Intuitively, where do you want
to move the query back to?
If you want to think more
you can pause the video.
Now if you think about
this picture you can realize that
in order to work well in this case
you want the query vector to be as close
to the positive vectors as possible.
That means, ideally you want to place
the query vector somewhere here or
we want to move the query
vector closer to this point.
Now, so what exactly at this point?
Well, if you want these relevant
documents to be ranked on the top
you want this to be in the center of
all of these relevant documents, right?
Because then if you draw
a circle around this one
you get all these relevant documents.
So that means we can move the query
back toward the centroid of
all the relevant document vectors.
And this is basically the idea of Rocchio,
of course you then can see that
the centroid of negative documents.
And one move away from
the negative documents.
Now geometrically we're
talking about a moving vector
closer to some other vector and
away from other vectors.
Algebraically it just means
we have this formula.
Here you can see this is
original query vector and
this average basically is the centroid
vector of relevant documents.
When we take the average
over these vectors
then we're computing
the centroid of these vectors.
And similarly this is the average in
that non-relevant document of vectors so
it's essentially of now random, documents.
And we have these three parameters here,
alpha, beta and gamma.
They're controlling
the amount of movement.
When we add these two vectors together
we're moving the query at the closer
to the centroid, alright, so
when we add them, together.
When we subtracted this part we kind
of move the query vector away from that
centroid so
this is the main idea of Rocchio Feedback.
And after we have done this we
will get a new query vector
which can use it to store documents.
This new New query vector will then
reflect the move of this
Original query vector toward
this Relevant centroid vector and
away from the Non-relevant
centroid vector, okay?
So let's take a look at example, right?
This is the example that we have seen
earlier only that I in the, the display
of the actual documents I only showed the
vector representation of these documents.
We have five documents here and we have
true red in the documents here, right?
They are displayed in red and
these are the term vectors.
Now, I just assumed an idea of weights,
a lot of times we have
zero weights of course.
These are negative documents, there
are two here, there is another one here.
Now in this Rocchio method we
first compute the centroid of
each category and so let's see.
Look at the centroid of
the positive document but
we simply just so it's very easy to see.
We just add this with this one
the corresponding element and
that's down here and take the average.
And then we're going to add
the corresponding elements and
then just take the average, right?
So we do this for all these.
In the end, what we have is this one.
This is the average vector of these two so
it's a centroid of these two, right?
Let's also look at the centroid
of the nested documents.
This is basically the same we're going to
take the average of three elements.
And these are the corresponding
elements in these three vectors and
so on and so forth.
So in the end, that we have this one.
Now, in the Rocchio feedback
method we're going to combine all
these with original query vector,
which is this.
So now let's see how we
combine them together.
Well, that's basically this, right?
So we have a parameter outlier controlling
the original query term weight that's 1.
And now I've beta to control
the inference of the positive
centroid Vector weight that's
1.5 that comes from here, right?
So this goes here and
we also have this negative wait here.
Conduit by a gamma here and
this weight has come from of
course the nective centroid here.
And we do exactly the same for
other terms each is for one term.
And this is our new vector.
And we're going to use this new query
vector, this one to run the documents.
You can imagine what would happen, right?
Because of the movement that this one or
the match of these red
documents much better.
Because we move this
vector closer to them and
it's going to penalize these black
documents, these non-relevant documents.
So this is precisely what
we want from feedback.
Now of course, if we apply this method in
practice we will see one potential problem
and that is the original query has
only four times that are not zero.
But after we do queries,
imagine you can imagine we'll have many
terms that would have a number of weights.
So the calculation would
have to involve more terms.
In practice,
we often truncate this vector and
only retain the terms which
is the highest weight.
So let's talk about how we
use this method in practice.
I just mentioned that we often truncate
the vector consider only a small number
of words that have highest
weights in the centroid vector.
This is for efficiency concern.
I also say that here that a negative
examples or non-relevant examples
tend not to be very useful especially
compared with positive examples.
Now you can think about the, why.
One reason is because negative documents
tend to distract the query in
all directions so when you take
the average it doesn't really tell you
where exactly it should be moving to.
Whereas, positive documents tend
to be clustered together and
they respond to you to
consistent the direction.
So that also means that sometimesw we
don't have those negative examples but
note that in,
in some cases in difficult queries where
most top random results are negative.
Negative feedback
afterwards is very useful.
Another thing is to avoid
over-fitting that means we have to
keep relatively high weight
on the original query terms.
Why?
Because the sample that we see in
feedback is a relatively small sample.
We don't want to overly
trust the small sample and
the original query terms
are still very important.
Those terms are typed in by the user and
the user has decided that those
terms are most important.
So in order to prevent the us
from over-fitting or drifting.
A type of drift prevent type of
drifting due to the bias toward the,
the feedback examples.
We generally would have to keep a pretty
high weight on the original terms so
it is safe to do that.
And this is especially, true for
pseudo awareness feedback.
Now this method can be used for
both relevance feedback and
pseudo relevance feedback.
In the case of pseudo feedback,
the parameter beta should be set to a,
a smaller value because
the random examples are assumed
to be random there not as reliable
as your relevance feedback, right?
In the case of relevance feedback,
we obviously could use a larger value.
So, those parameters
still have to be set and.
And the ro, Rocchio method is
usually robust and effective.
It's, it's still a very popular method for
feedback.
[MUSIC]