This lecture is about the web search.
In this lecture we
are going to talk about one of
the most important applications of
text retrieval, web search engines.
So let's first look at some
general challenges and
opportunities in web search.
Now, many information retrieval
algorithms had been developed at the,
before the web was born.
So, when the web was born,
it created the best opportunity to apply
those algorithms to major application
problem that everyone would care about.
So naturally, there had to be some
further extensions of the classical
search algorithms to address some new
challenges encountered in web search.
So here are some general challenges.
Firstly, this is a scalability challenge.
How we handle the size of the web,
and ensure completeness of
coverage of all the information.
How to serve many users quickly,
and by answering all their queries.
All right, so, that's one major challenge.
And before the web was born,
the scale of search was relatively small.
The second problem is that there
is low quality information.
And there are often spams.
The third challenge is
dynamics of the web.
The new pages are constantly created and
some pages may be updated,
eve-, very quickly.
So it makes it harder to,
keep the index fresh.
So these are some of
the challenges that the,
we have to solve in order to,
build a high quality web search engine.
On the other hand, there are also some
interesting opportunities that we can
leverage to improve search results.
There are many additional heuristics.
For example you know using links that
we can leverage to improve scoring.
Now the errors that we talked about such
as the vector space model are general
algorithms.
And they can be applied to any search
applications, so that's, the advantage.
On the other hand, they also don't take
advantage of special characteristics
of pages, or documents, in the specific
applications such as web search.
Web pages are linked with each other so
obviously the linking is something
that we can also leverage.
So because of these challenges and
opportunities there are new techniques
that have been developed for web search,
or due to the need of a web search.
One is parallel indexing and searching,
and this is to address the issue of
scalability, in particular
Google's imaging of MapReduce
is very inferential, and
has been very helpful in that aspect.
Second, there are techniques
that are developed for,
addressing the problem of spams.
So, spam detection.
We'll have to prevent those,
spam pages from being ranked high.
And there are also techniques
to achieve robust ranking.
And we're going to use a lot
of signals to rank pages so
that it's not easy to spam the search
engine with particular tricks.
And the third line of
techniques is link analysis.
And these are techniques
that can allow us to
to improve search results by
leveraging extra information.
And in general in web
search we're going to use
multiple features for ranking.
Not just link analysis but
also exploiting all kinds of crawls like
the layout of web pages or anchor text
that describes a link to another page.
So here's a picture showing the basic
search engine technologies.
Basically, this is the web on the left and
then user on the right side.
And we're going to help these, this
user get access to the web information.
And the first component is the crawler
that with the crawl pages and
the second component is indexer.
That will take these pages
create an invert index.
The third component that is a retrieval,
not with the using,
but the index to answer user's query,
by talking to the user's browser.
And then, the search results would be,
given to the user.
And, and then the browser
will show those results and,
to allow the user to
interact with the web.
So we're going to talk about
each of these component.
First we're going to talk about
the crawler also called a spider or
a software robot that would do something
like a crawling pages on the web.
To build a toy crawler is relatively easy
because you just need to start with a set
of seed pages and then fetch pages from
the web and parse these pages new links.
And then add them to the priority of q and
then just explore those additional links,
right.
But to build a real crawler
actually is tricky and
there are some complicated issues
that we have do deal with.
For example robustness,
what if the server doesn't respond.
What if there's a trap that generates
dynamically generated webpages that might,
attract your crawler to keep
crawling the same site and
to fetch dynamically generated pages.
The results of this issue of crawling and
you don't want to overload one particular
server with many crawling requests.
And you have to respect the,
the robot exclusion protocol.
You also need to handle
different types of files.
There are images, PDF files,
all kinds of formats on the web.
And you have to also
consider URL extensions.
So, sometimes those are cgi scripts, and,
you know, internal references, etc., and
sometimes, you have JavaScripts on the
page that, they also create challenges.
And you ideally should also
recognize [INAUDIBLE] the pages
because you don't have to
duplicate to the, those pages.
And finally, you may be interesting
to discover hidden URLs.
Those are URLs that may not be linked,
to any page.
But if you truncate the URL to,
shorter pass,
you might be able to get
some additional pages.
So, what are the major
crawling strategies?
In general, Breadth-First, is most common,
because it naturally balance,
balances server load.
You would not, keep probing
a particular server [INAUDIBLE].
Also parallel crawling is very natural,
because this task is very easy
to parallelise and there are some
variations of the crawling task.
One interesting variation
is called focused crawling.
In this kind we're going to crawl just
some pages about a particular topic.
For example, all pages about automobiles.
And, and, this is typically
going to start with a query,
and then you can use the query
to get some results.
From the major search engine.
And then you can start it with those
results and gradually crawl more.
So one challenge in crawling is to find
the new pages that people have created,
and people probably are creating
new pages all the time, and this is
very challenging if the new pages have
not been actually linked to any old page.
If they are, then you can probably refine
them by recrawling the older page.
So these are also some um,interesting
challenges that have to be solved.
And finally we might face the scenario of
incremental crawling or repeated crawling.
Right?
So your first,
let's say if you want to be
able to web search engine.
And you were the first to crawl
a lot of data from the web.
And then, but then once you
have collected all the data and
in future we just need to crawl the,
the update pages.
You, you, in general you don't have
to re-crawl everything, right?
Or it's not necessary.
So, in this case you,
you go as you minimize a resource overhead
by using minimum resource to,
to just still crawl updated pages.
So this is after a very interesting
research question here.
And [INAUDIBLE] research
question is that there aren't
many standard algorithms [INAUDIBLE] for
doing this, this task.
Right?
But in general, you can imagine,
you can learn from the past experience.
Right.
So the two major factors that
you have to consider are first,
will this page be updated frequently?
And do I have to crawl this page again?
If the page is a static page
that hasn't been changed for
months you probably don't have
to re-crawl it everyday, right?
Because it's unlikely that it
will be changed frequently.
On the other hand if it's you know,
sports score page that gets
updated very frequently and
you may need to re-crawl it maybe
even multiple times, on the same day.
The other factor to consider is,
is this page frequently accessed by users?
If it, if it is,
that means it's a high utility page, and
then thus it's more important to
ensure such a page to be fresh.
Compare it with another page that has
never been fetched by any users for
a year.
Than, even though that page
has been changed a lot, then,
it's probably not necessary to crawl that
page or at least it's not as urgent as,
to maintain the freshness of
frequently accessed page by users.
So to summarize,
web search is one of the most important
applications of text retrieval.
And there are some new challenges
particularly scalability,
efficiency, quality information.
There are also new opportunities
particularly, rich link information and
layout, et cetera.
Crawler is an essential component
of web search applications.
And, in general,
we can classify two scenarios.
Once is initial crawling and
here we want to have complete crawling
of the web if you are doing
a general search engine or
focus crawling if you want to just
target it at a certain type of pages.
And then there is another scenario that's
incremental updating of the crawl data or
incremental crawling.
In this case you need to
optimize the resource.
For to use minimum resource
we get the [INAUDIBLE]
[MUSIC].