[SOUND].
This lecture is about web indexing.
In this lecture, we will continue
talking about web search, and
we're going to talk about how
to create a web scale index.
So once we crawl the web
we've got a lot of web pages.
The next step is we use the indexer
to create the inverted index.
In general, we can use the standard
information retrieval techniques for
creating the index, and that is what we
talked about in the previous lecture.
But there are new challenges that we
have to solve for web scale indexing,
and the two main challenges of
scalability and efficiency.
The index will be so large that it cannot
actually fit into any single machine or
single disk, so we have to store
the data on multiple machines.
Also, because the data is so large,
it's beneficial to process the data in
parallel so
that we can produce the index quickly.
To address these challenges,
Google has made a number of innovations.
One is the Google File System,
that's a general distributed file system
that can help programmers manage files
stored on a cluster of machines.
The second is MapReduce.
This is a general software framework for
supporting parallel computation.
Hadoop is the most well known open
source implementation of MapReduce,
now used in many applications.
So this is the architecture
of the Google File System.
It uses a very simple centralized
management mechanism to manage
all the specific locations of files.
So it maintains the file namespace and
look up table to know where
exactly each file is stored.
The application client would
then talk to this GFS master.
And that obtains specific locations of
the files that they want to process.
And once the GFS client obtained
the specific information about the files,
then the application client
can talk to the specific
servers where the data
actually sits directly.
So that you can avoid avoid involving
other nodes in the network.
So when this file system
stores the files on machines
the system also would create
a fixed sizes of chunks.
So the data files are separate
into many chunks,
each chunk is 64 megabytes,
so it's pretty big.
And that's appropriate for
large data processing.
These chunks are replicated
to ensure reliability.
So this is something that the, the
programmer doesn't have to worry about,
and it's all taken care
of by this file system.
So from the application perspective,
the programmer would see this
as if it's a normal file.
The program doesn't have to know
where exactly it's stored, and
can just invoke high level
operators to process the file.
And another feature is that the data
transfer is directly between
application and chunk servers, so
it's, it's efficient in this sense.
On top of the Google file system, and
Google also proposed MapReduce as
a general framework for
parallel programming.
Now, this is very useful to support
a task like building inverted index.
And so this framework is hiding a lot of
low level features from the programmer.
As a result, the programmer can
make minimum effort to create
a application that can be run
on a large cluster in parallel.
So, some of the low level
details hidden in the framework,
including the specific natural
communications, or load balancing,
or where the tasks are executed, all these
details are hidden from the programmer.
There is also a nice feature which
is the built-in fault tolerance.
If one server is broken,
let's say, so it's down, and
then some tasks may not be finished,
then the MapReduce mechanism would
know that the task has not been done.
So it would automatically dispatch the
task on other servers that can do the job.
And therefore, again, the programmer
doesn't have to worry about that.
So here's how MapReduce works.
The input data will be separated
into a number of key, value pairs.
Now, what exactly is in the value
will depend on the data.
And it's actually a fairly
general framework to allow you to
just partition the data
into different parts.
And each part can be then
processed in parallel.
Each key, value pair will be
then sent to a map function.
The programmer will write
the map function, of course.
And then the map function will then
process this key value pair and
generate the,
a number of other key value pairs.
Of course, the new key is usually
different from the old key
that's given to the map as input.
And these key value pairs
are the output of the map function.
And all the outputs of all the map
functions will be then collected.
And then they will be further
sorted based on the key.
And the result is that all the values
that are associated with the same
key will be then grouped together.
So now we've got a pair of a key and a set
of values that are attached to this key.
So this will then be sent
to a reduce function.
Now, of course, each reduce function will
handle a different each a different key.
So we will send this,
these output values to
multiple reduce functions,
each handling a unique key.
A reduce function would then process
the input, which is a key and
a set of values, to produce another
set of key values as the output.
So these output values would be then
collected together to form the,
the final output.
Right, so this is the,
the general framework of MapReduce.
Now, the programmer only needs to
write the the map function and
the reduce function.
Everything else is actually taken
care of by the MapReduce framework.
So, you can see the programmer really
only needs to do minimum work.
And with such a framework, the input data
can be partitioned into multiple parts.
Each is processed in
parallel first by map, and
then in the process after
we reach the reduce stage,
then much more reduce functions
can also further process
the different keys and
their associated values in parallel.
So it achieves some it
achieves the purpose of parallel
processing of a large dataset.
So let's take a look at a simple example,
and that's word counting.
The input is is files containing words.
And the output that we want to generate is
the number of occurrences of each word, so
it's the word count.
Right, we know this,
this kind of counting would be useful to,
for example, assess the popularity
of a word in a large collection.
And this is useful for achieving
a factor of IDF weighting for search.
So how can we solve this problem?
Well, one natural thought is that,
well, this task can be done in
parallel by simply counting different
parts of the file in parallel and
then in the end,
we just combine all the counts.
And that's precisely the idea of
what we can do with MapReduce.
We can parallelize lines
in this input file.
So more specifically, we can assume
the input to each map function
is a key value pair that represents the
line number and the stream on that line.
So the first line, for
example, has a key of one.
And the value is Hello World Bye World,
and just four words on that line.
So this key-value pair will
be sent to a map function.
The map function would then just
count the words in this line.
And in this case, of course,
there are only four words.
Each word gets a count of one.
And these are the output that you see here
on this slide, from this map function.
So, the map function
is really very simple.
If you look at the, what the pseudocode
looks like on the right side, you see,
it simply needs to iterate over
all the words in this line,
and then just call a Collect function,
which means it would then send the word
and the counter to the collector.
The collector would then try to
sort all these key value pairs
from different map functions.
Right?
So the functions are very simple.
And the programmer specifies this function
as a way to process each part of the data.
Of course, the second line will be
handled by a different map function,
which will produce a similar output.
Okay, now the output from the map
functions will be then sent to
a collector.
And the collector will do
the internal grouping or sorting.
So at this stage, you can see we
have collected multiple pairs.
Each pair is a word and
its count in the line.
So once we see all these these pairs,
then we can sort them based on the key,
which is the word.
So we will collect all the counts of
a word, like bye, here, together.
And similarly, we do that for other words.
Like Hadoop, hello, etc.
So each word now is attached to
a number of values, a number of counts.
And these counts represent the occurrences
of this word in different lines.
So now we have got a new pair of a key and
a set of values,
and this pair will then be
fed into a reduce function.
So the reduce function now will
have to finish the job of counting
the total occurrences of this word.
Now it has already got all
these partial counts, so
all it needs to do is
simply to add them up.
So the reduce function shown
here is very simple as well.
You have a counter and then iterate over
all the words that you see in this array,
and then you just accumulate these counts,
right.
And then finally, you output the key and
and the total count,
and that's precisely what we want as
the output of this whole program.
So, you can see, this is already very
similar to building a inverted index,
and if you think about it,
the output here is indexed by a word, and
we have already got a dictionary,
basically.
We have got the count.
But what's missing is the document IDs and
the specific
frequency counts of words
in those documents.
So we can modify this slightly to actually
build a inverted index in parallel.
So here's one way to do that.
So in this case, we can assume
the input to a map function is a pair
of a key which denotes the document ID and
the value denoting the string for
that document.
So it's all the words in that document.
And so the map function will
do something very similar to
what we have seen in
the water company example.
It simply groups all the counts of
this word in this document together.
And it will then generate
a set of key value pairs.
Each key is a word.
And the value is the count of this word
in this document plus the document ID.
Now, you can easily see why we
need to add document ID here.
Of course, later, in the inverted index,
we would like to keep this information, so
the map function should keep track of it.
And this can then be sent to
the reduce function later.
Now, similarly another document D2
can be processed in the same way.
So in the end, again, there is a sorting
mechanism that would group them together.
And then we will have just
a key like java associated
with all the documents
that match this key, or
all the documents where java occurred,
and their counts,
right, so
the counts of java in those documents.
And this will be collected together.
And this will be, so
fed into the reduced function.
So, now you can see,
the reduce function has already got input
that looks like a inverted index entry,
right?
So, it's just the word and all
the documents that contain the word and
the frequency of the word
in those documents.
So, all you need to do is simply to
concatenate them into a continuous chunk
of data, and this can be then
retained into a file system.
So basically, the reduce function
is going to do very minimal work.
And so, this is pseudo-code for
inverted index construction.
Here we see two functions,
procedure Map and procedure Reduce.
And a programmer would specify these two
functions to program on top of MapReduce.
And you can see, basically,
they are doing what I just described.
In the case of Map,
it's going to count the occurrences
of a word using an associative array,
and will output all the counts
together with the document ID here.
Right?
So this,
the reduce function,
on the other hand simply concatenates
all the input that it has been given and
then put them together as one
single entry for this key.
So this is a very simple
MapReduce function, yet
it would allow us to construct an inverted
index at a very large scale, and
data can be processed
by different machines.
The program doesn't have to
take care of the details.
So this is how we can do parallel
index construction for web search.
So to summarize, web scale indexing
requires some new techniques that
go beyond the standard
traditional indexing techniques.
Mainly, we have to store index on
multiple machines, and this is usually
done by using a file system like Google
File System, a distributed file system.
And secondly, it requires creating
the index in parallel, because it's so
large, it takes a long time to create
an index for all the documents.
So if we can do it in parallel,
it would be much faster, and
this is done by using
the MapReduce framework.
Note that the both the GFS and
MapReduce frameworks are very general, so
they can also support
many other applications.
[MUSIC]