[SOUND].
So let's take a look at this in detail.
So in this random surfing model.
And any page would assume random surfer
would choose the next page to visit.
So this is a small graph here.
That's, of course an oversimplification
of the complicate it well.
But let's say there
are four documents here.
Right, D1, D2, D3 and D4.
And let's assume that a random surfer or
random walker can be any of these pages.
And then the random surfer could decide
to just randomly jump into any page.
Or follow a link and
then visit the next page.
So if the random server is at d1.
Then, you know, with some probability
that random surfer will follow the links.
Now there two outlinks here.
One is pointing to this D3.
The other is pointing to D4.
So the random surfer could pick any
of these two to reach e3 and d4.
But it also assumes that the random
surfer might, get bored sometimes.
So the random surfer would decide
to ignore the actual links, and
simply randomly jump to
any page on the web.
So, if it does that, eh,
it would be able to reach
any of the other pages even though there
is no link directly from to that page.
So this is the assume the randoms of.
Imagine a random server is
really doing surfing like this,
then we can ask the question.
How likely on average
the server would actually reach
a particular page d1, or d2, or d3.
That's the average probability
of visiting a particular page.
And this probability is precisely
what page rank computes.
So the page rank score of the document
is the average probability
that the surfer visits a particular page.
Now, intuitively this will basically
kept you the [INAUDIBLE] link account.
Why?
Because if a page has
a lot of in-links then
it would have a higher chance of being
visited, because there will be more
opportunities of having the surfer to
follow a link to come to this page.
And this is why
the random surfing model actually captures
the idea of counting the in links.
Note that is also considers
the indirect in links.
Why?
Because if the pages that point to you
have themselves a lot of in links,
that would mean the random server
would very likely reach one of them.
And therefore it increases
the chance of visiting you.
So this is a nice way to capture
both indirect and direct links.
So mathematically, how can we compute
this problem enough to see that we need
to take a look at how this
problem [INAUDIBLE] in computing.
So first let's take a look at
the transition matching sphere.
And this is just a matrix with
values indicating how likely a rand,
the random surfer will go
from one page to another.
So each rule stands for a starting page.
For example,
rule one would indicate the probability
of going to any other four pages from e1.
And here we see there are only
non two non zero entries.
Each is 1 over 2, a half.
So this is because if you look at
the graph, d1 is pointing to d3 and d4.
There's no link from d1 to d1 server or
d2,
so we've got 0s for
the first two columns and
0.5 for d3 and d4.
In general, the M in this matrix
M sub i j is the probability
of going from d, i, to d, j.
And obviously for each rule,
the values should sum to one,
because the surfer will have to go to
precisely one of these other pages.
Right?
So this is a transition matrix.
Now how can we compute the probability
of a server visiting a page?
Well if you look at the,
the server model, then basically
we can compute the probability
of reaching a page as follows.
So, here on the left-hand side,
you see it's the probability of
visiting page DJ at time t plus 1
because it's the next time cont.
On the right hand side, you can see
the question involves the probability
of, at page ei at time t.
So you can see the subsequent index t,
here.
And that indicates that's the probability
that the server was at
a document at time t.
So the equation basically captures
the two possibilities of
reaching at d j at time t plus 1.
What are these two possibilities?
Well one is through random surfing, and
one is through following
a link as we just explained.
So the first part captures the probability
that the random server would reach
this page by following a link.
And you can see, and
the random surfer chooses this
strategy was probably
the [INAUDIBLE] as we assumed.
And so
there is a factor of one minus alpha here.
But the main part is really
sum over all the possible
pages that the server could
have been at time t, right?
There were N pages, so
it's a sum over all the possible N pages.
Inside the sum is the product
of two probabilities.
One is the probability that
the server was at d i at time t.
That's p sub t of d i.
The other is the transition
probability from di to dj.
And so in order to reach this dj page,
the surfer must first be at di at time t.
And then also would have to follow
the link to go from di to dj,
so the probability is the probability
of being at di at time t, not divide by
the probability of, going from that
page to the top of the page dj here.
The second part is a similar sum.
The only difference is that now
the transition probability is uniform,
transition probability.
1 over n.
And this part captures the probability of
reaching this page,
through random jumping.
Right.
So, the form is exactly the same.
And in, in, this also allows us to see
why PageRank essentially assumes
smoothing of the transition matrix.
If you think about this 1 over N as
coming from another transition matrix
that has all the elements being 1 over N,
the uniform matrix.
Then you can see very clearly
essentially we can merge the two parts.
Because they are of the same form,
we can imagine there's a difference of
metrics that's a combination of this m and
that uniform matrix where
every element is 1 over n.
In this sense,
page one uses this idea of smoothing and
ensuring that there's no 0,
entry in such a transition matrix.
Of course this is, time depend,
calculation of probabilities.
Now, we can imagine if we want to
compute average probabilities,
the average probabilities probably
would satisfy this equation
without considering the time index.
So let's drop the time index and
just assume that they would be equal.
Now this would give us N equations.
Because for
each page we have such a equation.
And if you look at the what variables
we have in these equations,
there are also precisely N variables,
right?
So this basically means
we now have a system of
n equations with n variables,
and these are linear equations.
So basically, now the problem boils down
to solve this system of equations and
here I also show that
the equations in the metric form.
It's the vector P here equals a metrics or
the transports of the metrics here.
And multiply it by the vector again.
Now if you still remember some knowledge
that you learned from linear algebra and
then you will realize this is precisely
the equation for item vector.
Right?
When [INAUDIBLE] metrics by this method
you get the same value as this method.
And this can solved by using
an iterative algorithm.
So is it, because she's here, on the ball,
easily taken from the previous, slide.
So you see the, relationship between the,
the page source of different pages.
And in this iterative approach or
power approach
we simply start with, randomly the p.
And then we repeatedly just
updated this p by multiplying.
The metrics here by this P-Vector.
So I also show a concrete example here.
So you can see this now, if we assume.
How far is point two.
Then with the example that
we show here on this slide
we have the original
transition metrics here.
Right?
That encodes, that encodes the graph.
The actual links.
And we have this smoothing
transition metrics,
uniform transition metrics,
representing random jumping.
And we can combine them together with
interpolation to form another
metrics that would be like this.
So essentially we can
imagine now the looks.
Like this can be captured by that.
There are virtual links
between all the pages now.
So the page rank algorithm will
just initialize the p vector first,
and then just computed
the updating of this p vector
by using this, metrics multiplication.
Now if you rewrite this metrics multi,
multiplication
in terms of just a,
an individual equations, you'll see this.
And this is a, basically,
the updating formula for
this particular page is a,
page ranking score.
So you can also see, even if you
want to compute the value of this
updated score for d1,
you basically multiple this rule.
Right?
By this column, I will take
the total product of the two, right?
And that will give us the value for
this value.
So this is how we updated the vector.
We started with some initial values for
these guys.
For, for this, and then,
we just revise the scores which
generate a new set of scores.
And the updated formula is this one.
So we just repeatedly apply this,
and here it converges.
And when the metrics is like this.
Where there is no zero values and
it can be guaranteed to converge.
And at that point we will just, have
the PageRank scores for all the pages.
Now we typically set the initial
values just to 1 over n.
So interestingly, this update
formula can be also interpreted as
propagating scores on the graph.
All right.
Can you see why?
Well if you look at this formula and
then compare that with this graph,
and can you imagine how we
might be able to interpret this
as essentially propagating
scores over the graph.
I hope you will see that indeed
we can imagine we have values
initialized on each of these page.
All right, so we can have values here
that say, that's one over four for each.
And then welcome to use these
matrix to update this, the scores.
And if you look at the equation here,
this one, basically we're
going to combine the scores
of the pages that possible would lead to,
reaching this page.
So we'll look at all the pages
that are pointing to this page.
And then combine their scores and
the propagated score,
the sum of the scores to this document D1.
We look after the, the scores
that represented the probability
that the random server would be visiting
the other pages before it reaches the D1.
And then just do the propagation
to simulate the probability
of reaching this, this page D 1.
So there are two interpretations here.
One is just the matrix multiplication.
And we repeated that.
Multiply the vector by this metrics.
The other is to just think of it as
propagating the scores repeatedly
on the web.
So in practice the composition of PageRank
score is actually efficient because
the metrices are sparse and there are some
ways to transform the equation so
you avoid actually literally computing
the values of all of those elements.
Sometimes you may also
normalize the equation, and
that will give you a somewhat
different form of the equation,
but then the ranking of
pages will not change.
The results of this potential
problem of zero out link problem.
In that case if the page does not have
any outlook, then the probability of
these pages will, will not sum to 1.
Basically, the probability of
reaching the next page from this
page will not sum to 1.
Mainly because we have lost some
probability mass when we assume that
there's some probability that
the server will try to follow links but
then there's no link to follow, right?
And one possible solution is simply to
use page specific damping factor and
that, that could easily fix this.
Basically that's to say, how far do we
want from zero for a page with no outlink.
In that case the server would just have to
render them [INAUDIBLE] to another page
instead of trying to follow the link.
So there are many extensions of page rank.
One extension is to do
top-specific page rank.
Note that page rank doesn't really
use the query format machine, right?
So, [INAUDIBLE] so we can make page rank,
appear specific, however.
So, for example,
in the topic specific page rank,
we can simply assume when the surfer,
is bored.
The surfer is not going to randomly
jump into any page on the web.
Instead, it's going to jump,
to only those pages that are to a query.
For example, if the query is about sports
then we could assume that when it's
doing random jumping, it's going
to randomly jump to a sports page.
By doing this then we canbuy
a PageRank to topic align with sports.
And then if you know the current query
is about sports then you can use this
specialized PageRank score
to rank the options.
That would be better than if you
use a generic PageRank score.
PageRank is also general algorithm
that can be used in many other.
Locations for network analysis, particular
for example for social networks.
We can imagine if you compute their
PageRank scores for social network,
where a link might indicate
friendship relation,
you'll get some meaningful scores for
people.
[MUSIC]