[SOUND].
This lecture is about link analysis for
web search.
In this lecture we're going to talk
about web search, and particularly
focusing on how to do link analysis and
use the results to improve search.
The main topic of this lecture is to look
at the ranking algorithms for web search.
In the previous lecture,
we talked about how to create index.
Now that we have got index,
we want to see how we can improve
ranking of pages on the web.
Standard IR models can
also be applied here,
in fact they are important building
blocks for supporting web search,
but they aren't sufficient,
mainly for the following reasons.
First, on the web we tend to have
very different information needs.
For example, people might search for
a web page or entry page, and
this is different from
the traditional library search
where people are primarily interested
in collecting literature information.
So these kind of queries are often
called navigational queries,
the purpose is to navigate into
a particular targeted page.
So for such queries, we might
benefit from using link information.
Secondly, documents have
additional information.
And on the web, web pages are web format.
There are a lot of other groups,
such as the layout, the title,
or link information again.
So this has provided an opportunity to
use extra context information of
the document to improve scoring.
And finally,
information quality varies a lot.
So that means we have to consider many
factors to improve the ranking algorithm.
This would give us a more robust way to
rank the pages making it the harder for
any spammer to just manipulate the one
signal to improve the ranking of a page.
So as a result people have made
a number of major extensions
to the ranking algorithms.
One line is to exploit links to
improve scoring and
that's the main topic of this lecture.
People have also proposed
algorithms to exploit large scale
implicit feedback information
in the form of clickthroughs.
That's of course in the category
of feedback techniques, and
machinery is often used there.
In general, in web search the ranking
algorithms are based on machinery
algorithms to combine
all kinds of features.
And many of them are based on the standard
original models such as BM25 that
we talked about, or
queried iCode to score
different parts of documents or
to, provide additional features
based on content matching.
But link information
is also very useful so
they provide additional scoring signals.
So let's look at links in
more detail on the web.
So this is a snapshot of some
part of the web, let's say.
So we can see there are many links
that link different pages together.
And in this case you can also look at the,
the center here.
There is a description of a link
that's pointing to the document on
the right side.
Now this description text
is called anchor text.
If you think about this text,
it's actually quite useful
because it provides some extra description
of that page being pointed to.
So, for example, if someone wants
to bookmark Amazon.com front page,
the person might say,
the big online bookstore, and
then with a link to Amazon, right?
So the description here is actually very
similar to what the user would type in
in the query box when they are looking for
such a page.
That's why it's very useful for,
for, ranking pages.
Suppose someone types in a query
like online bookstore or
big online bookstore, right.
The query would match this
anchor text in the page here.
And then this actually
provides evidence for
matching the page that's been pointed to,
that is the Amazon entry page.
So if you match the anchor text
that describes the link to a page,
actually that provides good evidence for
the relevance of the page
being pointing to.
So anchor text is very useful.
If you look at the bottom part of this
picture, you can also see there are some
patterns of links, and these links might
indicate the utility of a document.
So for example,
on the right side you can see this
page has received many in, in links.
That means many other pages
are pointing to this page.
And this shows that this
page is quite useful.
On the left side you can see, this is
a page that points to many other pages.
So, this is a theater page
that would allow you to
actually see a lot of other pages.
So we can call the first case authority
page and the second case a hub page.
This means the link information
can help in two ways.
One is to provide extra text for matching.
The other is to provide some
additional scores for the web
pages to characterize how likely a page is
a hub, how likely a page is a authority.
So people then, of course, propose ideas
to leverage this, this link information.
Google's PageRank,
which was a main technique that they
used in early days, is a good example.
And that, that is the algorithm
to capture page popularity,
basically to score authority.
So the intuitions here are, links are just
like citations in the literature.
Think about one page
pointing to another page.
This is very similar to one
paper citing another paper.
So, of course,
then if a page is cited often,
then we can assume this page to
be more useful in general, right?
So that's a very good intuition.
Now, page rank is essentially
to take advantage of this
intuition to implement the,
with the principle approach.
Intuitively it's essentially doing
citation counting or in link counting.
It just improves this simple idea in,
in two ways.
One is would consider indirect citations.
So that means you don't just look
at the how many in links you have,
you also look at the what are those
pages that are pointing to you.
If those pages, themselves, have a lot
of in links, well that means a lot.
In some sense you will get
some credit from that.
But if those pages that are pointing
to you are not are being pointed to
by other pages, they themselves don't
have many in links, then, well,
you don't get that much credit.
So that's the idea of
getting indirect citation.
Right, so you can also understand
this idea by looking at, again,
the research papers.
If you are cited by, let's say ten papers,
and those ten papers are, just
workshop papers and that, or some papers
that are not very influential, right,
so although you got ten in links,
that's not as good as if you have,
you're cited by ten papers that themselves
have attracted a lot of other citations.
So this is a case where
we would like to consider indirect
links and PageRank does that.
The other idea is,
it's good to smooth the citations.
Or, or, or
assume that basically every page is
having a non-zero pseudo citation count.
Essentially, you are trying to imagine
there are many virtual links that
will link all the pages together so
that you,
you actually get pseudo
citations from everyone.
The, the reason why they want to
do that is this would allow them
to solve the problem elegantly
with linear algebra technique.
So I think maybe the best
way to understand the page
rank is through think of
this as through computer,
the probability of a random surfer,
visiting every web page, right.
[MUSIC]