[SOUND] So
now let's take a look at the specific,
method that's based on regression.
Now this is one of the many
different methods in fact,
it's the one of the simplest methods.
And I choose this to explain the idea
because it's it's so simple.
So in this approach we simply assume
that the relevance of a document
with respect to the query, is related to
a linear combination of all the features.
Here I used the Xi to emote the feature.
So Xi of Q and D is a feature.
And we can have as many features as,
we would like.
And we assume that these features
can be combined in a linear manner.
And each feature is controlled
by a parameter here.
And this beta is a parameter,
that's a weighting parameter.
A larger value would mean the feature
would have a higher weight and
it would contribute more
to the scoring function.
The specific form of the function
actually also involves
a transformation of
the probability of relevance.
So this is the probability of relevance.
We know that the probability of relevance
is within the range from 0 to 1.
And we could have just assumed
that the scoring function is
related to this linear combination.
Right, so we can do a,
a linear regression but
then the value of this linear
combination could easily go beyond 1.
So this transformation here would map ze,
0 to 1 range through the whole
range of real values.
You can, you can verify it,
it by yourself.
So this allows us then to connect
to the probability of relevance
which is between 0 and 1 to a linear
combination of arbitrary efficients.
And if we rewrite this into a probability
function, we will get the next one.
So on this side on this equation,
we will have the probability of relevance.
And on the right hand side,
we will have this form.
Now this form is created non-active.
And it still involves the linear
combination of features.
And it's also clear that is,
if this value is,
is.
Of the linear combination
in the equation above.
If this this, this value here,
if this value is large then it
will mean this value is small.
And therefore, this probability,
this whole probability, would be large.
And that's what we expect.
Basically, it would be if this
combination gives us a high value,
then the document's more likely relevant.
So this is our hypothesis.
Again, this is not necessarily
the best hypothesis.
That this is a simple way to connect
these features with
the probability of relevance.
So now we have this this
combination function.
The next task is to see how we
need to estimate the parameters so
that the function can truly be applied.
Right.
Without them knowing
that they have values, it's,
it's harder to apply this function, okay.
So let's how we can estimate, beta values.
All right.
Let's take a look, at a simple example.
In this example, we have three features.
One is BM25 score of
the document under the query.
One is the page rank score of
the document, which might or
might not depend on the query.
Hm, we might have a top
sensitive page rank.
That would depend on the query.
Otherwise, the general page rank
doesn't really depend on the query.
And then we have BM25 score on
the Anchor task of the document.
These are then the feature values for
a particular doc, document query pair.
And in this case the document is D1.
And the,
the judgment says that it's relevant.
Here's another training instance,
and these features values.
But in this case it's non-relevant, okay?
This is a overly simplified case,
where we just have two instances.
But it,
it's sufficient to illustrate the point.
So what we can do is we use the maximum
likelihood estimator to actually estimate
the parameters.
Basically, we're going to do, predict
the relevance status of the document,
the, based on the feature values.
That is given that we observe
these feature values here.
Can we predict the relevance?
Yeah.
And of course, the prediction will be
using this function that you see here.
And we hypothesize this that
the probability of relevance is related
features in this way.
So we're going to see for
what values of beta we can
predict that the relevance well.
What do we mean?
Well, what, what do we mean by
predicting the relevance well?
Well we just mean.
In the first case for D1,
this expression here,
right here, should give higher values.
In fact, they would hope this
to give a value close to one.
Why?
Because this is a relevant document.
On the other hand, in the second case for
D2 we hope this value would be small.
Right.
Why?
It's because it's a non-relevant document.
So now let's see how this can
be mathematical expressed.
And this is similar to,
expressing the probability of a document.
Only that we are not talking about
the probability of words but
talking about the probability
of relevance, 1 or 0.
So what's the probability
of this document?
The relevant if it has
these feature values.
Well this is.
Just this expression, right?
We just need to pluck in the X, the Xis.
So that's what we'll get.
It's exactly like, what we have seen that,
only that we replace these Xis.
With now specific values.
And so, for example, this 0.7 goes
to here and this 0.11 goes to here.
And these are different feature values and
we'll combine them in this particular way.
The beta values are still unknown.
But this gives us the probability
that this document is relevant
if we assume such a model.
Okay, and
we want to maximize this probability since
this is a random document.
What we do for the second document.
Well, we want to compute to the
probability that the predictions is, is n,
non-relevant.
So, this would mean, we have to compute
a 1 minus, right this expression.
Since this expression.
Is actually the probability of relevance,
so to compute the non relevance
from relevance, we just do 1 minus
the probability of relevance, okay?
So this whole expression then.
Just is our probability of predicting
these two relevance values.
One is 1.
Here, one is a 0.
And this whole equation
is our probability.
Of observing a 1 here and
observing a 0 here.
Of course this probability depends
on the beta values, right?
So then our goal is to
adjust the beta values to make this
whole thing reach its maximum.
Make that as large as possible.
So that means we
are going to compute this.
The beta is just the, the parameter
values that would maximize this for
like holder expression.
And what it means is if
look at the function is
we're going to choose betas to
make this as large as possible.
And make this also as large as possible
which is equivalent to say make
this the part as small as possible.
And this is precisely what we want.
So once we do the training,
now we will know the beta values.
So then this function will be well
defined once their values are known.
Both this and
this will become pretty less specified.
So for any new query and new document we
can simply compute the features [NOISE]
For that pair and then we just use this
formula to generate a ranking score.
And this scoring function can be used in
for rank documents for a particular query.
So that's the basic idea of,
learning to rank.
[MUSIC]