[SOUND].
This lecture is about recommender systems.
So, so far we have talked about
a lot of aspects of search engines.
And we have talked about the problem
of search and the ranking problem,
different methods for ranking,
implementation of search engine and
how to evaluate the search engine,
et cetera.
This is partly because we know
that web search engines are,
by far, the most important
applications of text retrieval.
And they are the most useful tools
to help people convert big raw text
data into a small set
of relevant documents.
Another reason why we spend so
many lectures on search engines is because
many techniques used in search engines
are actually also very useful for
recommender systems,
which is the topic of this lecture.
And so overall the two systems
are actually well connected,
and there are many techniques
that are shared by them.
So this is a slide that you have
seen before when we talked about
the two different modes of
text access pull and push.
And, we mentioned that recommender
systems are the main systems to serve
users in the push mode, where
the systems will take the initiative to
recommend the information to user, or to
push the relevant information to the user.
And this often works well when the user
has a relatively stable information need,
when the system has good
knowledge about what a user wants.
So a recommender system is sometimes
called a filtering system.
And it's because recommending
useful items to people is like
discarding or
filtering out the useless articles.
So in this sense,
they are kind of similar.
And in all the cases,
the system must make a binary decision.
And usually, there is a dynamic
source of information items,
and you have some knowledge about the
user's interest, and then the system would
make a delivery decision, whether
this item is interesting to the user.
And then if it is interesting then
the system would recommend the article to
the user.
So the basic filtering question here is
really, will this user like, this item?
Will U like item X?
And there are two ways to answer this
question if you think about it, right?
One is look at what items U likes, and
then we can see if X is
actually like those items.
The other is to look at who likes X ,and
we can see if this user looks like a,
one of those users, or
like most of those users.
And these strategies can be combined.
If we follow the first strategy and
look at item similarity in the case
of recommended text objects,
then we are talking about a content-based
filtering or content-based recommendation.
If we look at the second strategy then,
this will compare users.
And in this case,
we're exploiting user similarity,
and the technique is often called
a collaborative filtering.
So let's first look at
the content-based filtering system.
This is what a system would look like.
Inside the system, there would be
a binary classifier that would have some
knowledge about the user's interests, and
it's called the user interest profile.
It maintains the profile to keep
track of the user's interest.
And then there is a utility function to
guide the user to make decisions, and
I'll explain the utility of
the function in a moment.
It helps the system decide
where to set the threshold.
And then the accepted documents
will be those that have passed
the threshold according to the classifier.
There should be also an initialization
module that would take a user's input,
maybe from a user's, specified keywords,
or a chosen category, et cetera.
And this will be, to feed the system
with a initial user profile.
There is also typically a learning
module that will learn from
users' feedback over time.
Now note that in this case, typically
users' information need is stable so
the system would have a lot of
opportunities to observe the users,
you know, if the user has taken
a recommended item as viewed that, and
this is a cu, a signal to indicate that
the recommended item may be relevant.
If the user discarded it,
no, it's not relevant.
And so, such feedback can be a long-term
feedback and can last for a long time and
the system can clock, collect a lot of
information about this user's interests.
And this can then be used
to improve the classifier.
Now whats the criteria for
evaluating such a system?
How do we know this filtering
system actually performs well?
Now in this case we cannot use the ranking
evaluation measures, like a map,
because we can't afford waiting for
a lot of documents,
and then rank the documents to
make a decision for the user.
And so, the system must make a decision,
in real time,
in general to decide whether the item
is above the threshold or not.
So in other words,
we're trying to decide absolute relevance.
So in this case one common use
strategy is to use a utility function
through a valid system.
So here I show a linear utility function
that's defined as, for example,
3 multiplied by the number of
good items that you delivered,
minus 2 multiplied by the number of bad
items you delete, that you delivered.
So in other words, we,
we could kind of just
treat this as almost a,
in a gambling game.
If you delete,
if you deliver one good item,
let's say you win $3, you gain $3.
But if you deliver a bad one,
you would lose $2.
And this utility function
basically kind of measures,
how much money you would,
get by doing this kind of game, right.
And so it's clear that if you want
to maximize this utility function,
your strategy should be to deliver
as many good articles as possible,
and minimize the delivery of bad articles.
That, that's obvious, right.
Now one interesting question here is,
how should we set these coefficients?
Now I just showed a 3 and a negative 2,
as the possible coefficients, but one can
ask the question, are they reasonable?
So what do you think?
Do you think that's a reasonable choice?
What about other choices?
So for example, we can have 10 and
minus 1, or 1 minus 10.
What's the difference?
What do you think?
How would this utility function affect
the system's threshold of this issue?
Right, you can think of these two extreme
cases, 10 minus 1 versus 1 minus 10.
Which one do we think it would
encourage the system to over-deliver?
And which one would encourage
the system to be conservative?
Yeah?
If you think about it, you will see
that when we get a big award for
delivering a good document, you incur only
a small penalty for delivering a bad one.
Intuitively, you would be
encouraging to deliver more, right?
And you can try to deliver more in hope
of getting a good one delivered, and
then you'll get a big award.
Right, so on the other hand,
if you choose 1 minus 10,
you don't really get such a big prize
if you deliver a good document.
On the other hand, you will have
a big loss if you deliver bad one.
You can imagine that the system
would be very reluctant to
deliver lot of documents.
It has to be absolutely sure
that it's a non-relevant one.
So this utility function has to be
designed based on a specific application.
The three basic problems in content-based
filtering are the following.
First has to make a filtering decision.
So it has to be a binary decision maker,
a binary classifier.
Given a text, a text document, and
a profile description of the user,
it has to say yes or no, whether this
document should be delivered or not.
So that's a decision module, and
there should be a initialization
module as you have seen earlier.
And this is to get the system started.
And we have to initialize the system based
on only very limited text description,
or very few examples from the user.
And the third component is
a learning module which ha,
has to be able to learn from limited
relevance judgments because we
can only learn from the user about their
preferences on the delivery documents.
If we don't deliver a document
to the user, we'd never know
we would never be able to know whether
the user likes it or not, right.
And we can accumulate a lot of documents,
we can learn from the entire history.
Now, all these models would have to
be optimized to maximize the utility.
So how can we build a such a system?
And there are many different approaches.
Here we are going to talk about
how to extend a retrieval system,
a search engine for information filtering.
Again, here's why we've spent a lot of
times talk about the search engines.
Because it's actually not very hard
to extend the search engine for
information filtering.
So, here is the basic idea for
extending a retrieval system for
information filtering.
First, we can reuse a lot of
retrieval techniques to do scoring.
All right, so we know how to score
documents against queries et cetera.
We can measure the similarity between
a profile text description and a document.
And then we can use a score threshold for
the filtering decision.
We, we do retrieval and then we kind
of find the scores of documents, and
then we apply a threshold to, to say,
to see whether a document is
passing this threshold or not.
And if it's passing the threshold,
we are going to say it's relevant and
we are going to deliver it to the user.
And another component that we have to add
is, of course, to learn from the history.
And here we can use the traditional
feedback techniques
to learn to improve scoring.
And we know Rocchio can be used for
scoring improvement, right?
And, but we have to develop new approaches
to learn how to set the threshold.
And you know,
we need to set it initially, and
then we have to learn how to
update the threshold over time.
So here's what the system
might look like if we just
generalized a vector-space model for
filtering problems, right?
So you can see the document vector could
be fed into a scoring module, which it
already exists in in a search engine
that implements a vector-space model.
And the profile will be treated
as a query essentially.
And then the profile vector can be
matched with the document vector,
to generate the score.
And then this score will be fed into
a thresholding module that would
say yes or no.
And then the evaluation would be based on
the utility for the filtering results.
If it says yes, and then the document
will be sent to the user, and
then the user could give some feedback.
And the feedback information would
have been use, would be used to both
adjust to the threshold and
adjust the vector representation.
So the vector learning is essentially
the same as query modification or
feedback in the case of search.
The threshold learning is a no,
new component in that we need
to talk a little bit more about.
[MUSIC]