[SOUND].
There are some interesting
challenges in threshold.
Would have known in the filtering problem.
So here I show the,
sort of the data that you can collect in,
in the filtering system.
So you can see the scores and
the status of relevance.
So the first one has a score 36.5,
and it's relevant.
The second one is not relevant.
Of course, we have a lot of documents for
which we don't know the status,
because we will have to the user.
So as you can see here,
we only see the judgements of
documents delivered to the user.
So this is not a random sample.
So it's a censored data.
It's kind of biased, so
that creates some difficulty for learning.
And secondly, there are in general very
little labeled data and very few relevant
data, so it's, it's also challenging for
machine learning approaches.
Typically they require
require more training data.
And in the extreme case at the beginning,
we don't even have any,
label there as well.
The system still has to make a decision,
so
that's a very difficult
problem at the beginning.
Finally, the results of this issue of
exploration versus exploitation tradeoff.
Now this means we also want to
explore the document space a little bit,
and to, to see if the user
might be interested in the documents
that we have not yet labeled.
So, in other words, we're going to
explore the space of user interests
by testing whether the user might be
interested in some other documents that
currently are not matching
the user's interest.
This so well.
So how do we do that?
Well we could lower the threshold a little
bit and do we just deliver some near
misses to the user to see what
the user would respond so
see how the user will,
would respond to this extra document.
And, and this is a trade off, because
on the one hand, you want to explore,
but on the other hand,
you don't want to really explore too much,
because then you would over-deliver
non-relevant information.
So exploitation means you would,
exploit what you learn about the user.
And let's say you know the user is
interested in this particular topic, so
you don't want to deviate that much.
And, but if you don't deviate at all,
then you don't explore at all.
That's also not good.
You might miss opportunity to learn
another interest of the user.
So this is a dilemma.
And that's also a difficult
problem to solve.
Now how do we solve these problems?
In general, I think why can't I used the
empirical utility optimization strategy?
And this strategy is basically to optimize
the threshold based on, historical data,
just as you have seen on
the previous slide, right?
So you can just compute the utility
on the training data for
each candidate score threshold.
Pretend that [INAUDIBLE]
cut at this point.
What if I cut out the [INAUDIBLE]
threshold, what would happen?
What's utility?
Compute the utility, right?
We know the status, what's it based on
approximation of click-throughs, right?
So then we can just choose this
threshold that gives the maximum
utility on the training data.
Now but this of course doesn't account for
exploration that we just talked about.
And there is also the difficulty of bias.
Training sample, as we mentioned.
So in general, we can only get an upper
bound or, for the true optimal threshold
because the, the al, the threshold
might be actually lower than this.
So it's possible that the discarded item
might be actually interesting to the user.
So how do we solve this problem?
Well we generally as I said we can lower
the threshold to explore a little bit.
So here's one particular approach called
the beta-gamma threshold learning.
So the, the idea is foreign.
So, here I show a ranked list of
all the training documents
that we have seen so far.
And they are ranked by their positions.
And on the Y-axis, we show the Utility.
Of course, this function depends on
how you specify the coefficients in
the Utility function.
But we can not imagine depending on the
cut off position we will have a utility.
That means suppose I cut at this
position and that will be the utility.
So we can for
example I then find some cut off point.
The optimal point theta
optimal is the point
when we would achieve the maximum
utility if we had chosen this threshold.
And there is also 0 threshold,
0 utility threshold.
As you can see at this cut off.
The utility is 0.
Now, what does that mean?
That means if I lower the threshold, and
then get the, and now I'm I reach this
threshold, the utility would be lower,
but it's still positive.
Still non-elective, at least.
So it's not as high as
the optimal utility, but
it gives us a a safe point
to explore the threshold.
As I just explained, it's desirable
to explore the interest space.
So it's desirable to lower the threshold
based on your training data.
So that means, in general, we want to set
the threshold somewhere in this range.
It's the when user off fault to
control the the deviation from
the optimal utility point.
So you can see the formula of the
threshold will be just the incorporation
of the zero utility threshold and
the optimal between the threshold.
Now the question is how,
how should we set r form, you know and
when should we deviate more
from the optimal utility point.
Well this can depend on multiple factors
and the one way to solve the problem is to
encourage this threshold
mechanism to explore
up the 0 point, and
that's a safe point, but
we're not going to necessarily
reach all the way to the 0 point.
But rather we're going to use other
parameters to further define alpha.
And this specifically is as follows.
So there will be a beta
parameter to control.
The deviation from the optimal threshold.
And this can be based on for
example can be accounting for
the over throughout
the training data let's say.
And so
this can be just the adjustment factor.
But what's more interesting is this gamma
parameter here, and you can see in this
formula gamma is controlling
the the influence
of the number of examples
in training data set.
So you can see in this formula as N which
denotes the number of training examples.
Becomes bigger than it would
actually encourage less exploration.
In other words, when N is very small,
it will try to explore more.
And that just means if we
have seen few examples,
we're not sure whether we have
exhausted the space of interests.
So [INAUDIBLE].
But as we have seen many examples
from the user, many data points,
then we feel that we probably
dont' have to explore more.
So this gives us a dynamic of strategy for
exploration, right?
The more examples we have seen,
the less exploration we are going to do.
So, the threshold will be closer
to the optimal threshold.
So, that's the basic
idea of this approach.
Now, this approach actually, has been
working well in some evaluation studies.
And, particularly effective.
And, also can welcome arbitrary utility
with a appropriate lower bound.
And explicitly addresses
exploration-exploration tradeoff.
And it kind of uses a zero in this
threshold point as a, a safeguard.
For exploration and exploiting tradeoff.
We're not, never going to explore
further than the zero utility point.
So, if you take the analogy of gambling,
and you,
you don't want to risk losing money.
You know, so it's a safe strategy,
a conservative strategy for exploration.
And the problem is, of course,
this approach is purely heuristic.
And the zero utility lower bound
is also often too conservative.
And there are, of course, calls
are more advanced than machine learning
projects that have been proposed for
solving these problems.
And this is a very active research area.
So to summarize there
are two strategies for
recommending systems or filtering systems.
One is content based,
which is looking at the item similarity.
And the other is collaborative filtering,
which is looking at the user similarity.
In this lecture we have covered
content-based filtering approach.
In the next lecture, we're going to
talk about collaborative filtering.
The content-based filtering
system we generally have to solve
several problems related to filtering
decision and learning, etc.
And such a system can actually
be based on a search engine
system by adding a threshold mechanism and
adding adaptive learning
algorithm to allow the system
to learn from long term
feedback from the user.
[MUSIC]