[NOISE].
And here what will do is
talk about basic strategy,
and that would be based on
similarity of users and
then predicting the rating
of an object by a, a,
active user using the ratings of
similar users to this active user.
This is called a memory-based approach
because it's a little bit similar to
storing all the user information.
And when we are considering a particular
user, we're going to try to
kind of retrieve the relevant users, or
the similar users through this user case.
And then try to use that
user's information about those users
to predict the preference of this user.
So here's the general idea, and
we use some notations here, so.
X sub i j denotes the rating
of object o j by user u i.
And n sub i is average rating
of all objects by this user.
So this n i is needed.
Because we would like to normalize
the ratings of objects by this user.
So how do you do normalization?
Well, where do you adjust that?
Subtract the,
the average rating from all the ratings.
Now this is the normalized ratings so
that the ratings from different
users will be comparable.
Because some users might be more generous
and they generally give more high ratings.
But, some others might be more critical.
So, their ratings can not be
directly compared with each other or
aggregated them together.
So, we need to do this normalization.
Now, the prediction of the rating.
On the item by another user or
active user, u sub a here
can be based on the average
ratings of similar users.
So the user u sub a is the user that we
are interested in recommending items to.
And we now are interested in
recommending this o sub j.
So we're interested in knowing how
likely this user will like this object.
How do we know that?
Well the idea here is to look at the how
whether similar users to this user
have liked this object.
So mathematically, this is, as you say,
the predict the rating of this
user on this app, object.
User A on object Oj is
basically combination of
the normalized ratings of different users.
And in fact, here,
we're picking a sum of all the users.
But not all users contribute
equally to the average.
And this is controlled by the weights.
So this.
Weight controls the inference
of a user on the prediction.
And of course, naturally this weight
should be related to the similarity
between ua and this particular user, ui.
The more similar they are then
the more contribution we would like
user u i to make in predicting
the preference of u a.
So the formula is extremely simple.
You're going to see it's a sum
of all the possible users.
And inside the sum, we have their ratings,
well their normalized
ratings as I just explained.
The ratings need to be normalized in
order to be comfortable with each other.
And then these ratings
are rated by their similarity.
So we can imagine a W of A and
I is just a similarity of user A user I.
Now, what's k here?
Well, k is a simpler normalizer.
It's just it's just one over the sum
of all the weights, over all the users.
And so this means, basically, if you
consider the weight here together with k.
And we have coefficients or weights
that would sum to one for all the users.
And it's just a normalization strategy,
so that you get this predicted rating
in the same range as the these ratings
that we use to make the prediction.
Right?
So, this is basically the main idea
of memory-based approaches for
collaborative filtering, okay?
Once we make this prediction,
we also would like to map back
to the rating that the user.
The user would actually make.
And this is to further add the,
mean rating or
average rating of this user u
sub a to the predicted value.
This would recover.
A meaningful rating for this user.
So if this user is generous,
then the average would be somewhat high,
and when we added that, the rating will
be adjusted to a relatively high rating.
Now, when you recommend an item to a user,
this actually doesn't really matter
because you are interested in basically
the normalized rating
that's more meaningful.
But when they evaluate these collaborative
filtering approach is typically
assumed that actual ratings of user
on these objects to be unknown.
And then you do the prediction and
then you compare the predicted
ratings with their actual ratings.
So they,
you do have access to the actual ratings.
But then you pretend you don't know.
And then you compare real systems
predictions with the actual ratings.
In that case, obviously the system's
prediction would have to be adjusted to
match the actual result the user, and this
is not what's happening here, basically.
Okay?
So this is the memory-based approach.
Now of course if you look at the formula,
if you want to write
the program to implement it.
You still face the problem of determining
what is this w function, right?
Once you know the w function, then
the formula is very easy to implement.
So indeed there are many different ways to
compute this function or this weight, w.
And, specific approaches generally
differ in how this is computed.
So, here are some possibilities.
And, you can imagine,
there are many pro, other possibilities.
One popular approach is we use
the Pearson Correlation Coefficient.
This would be a sum of a common
range of items, and the formula
is a standard Pearson correlation
coefficient formula, as shown here.
So, this basically measures
weather the two users tended
to all give higher ratings to similar
items, or lower ratings to similar items.
Another measure is the cosine measure and
this is the retreat the rating vectors as
vectors in the vector space, and then
we're going to measure the the angel and
compute the cosign of
the angle of the two vectors.
And this measure has been used in the
vector space more for retrieval as well.
So as you can imagine, there are so
many different ways of doing that.
In all these cases, note that the user
similarity is based on their preferences
on items, and we did not actually use
any content information of these items.
It didn't matter what these items are.
They can be movies, they can be books,
they can be products,
they can be tax documents.
We just didn't care about the content.
And so this allows such approach to be
applied to a wide range of problems.
Now in some newer approaches of course,
we would like to use more
information about the user.
Clearly, we know more about the user, not
just a, these preferences on these items.
And so in a actual filtering system, using
collaborative filtering, we could also
combine that with content-based filtering,
we could use context information.
And those are all interesting approaches
that people are still studying.
There are newer approaches proposed.
But this approach has been shown
to work reasonably well and
it's easy to implement.
And practical applications
could be a starting point to
see if the strand here works well for
your application.
So there are some obvious ways
to also improve this approach.
And mainly would like to improve
the user similarity measure.
And there are some practical
issues to deal with here as well.
So for example,
there will be a lot of missing values.
What do you do with them?
Well, you can set them to default values
or the average ratings of the user.
And that will be a simple solution.
But there are advantages to approaches
that can actually try to predict those
missing values and then use the predicted
values to improve the similarity.
So in fact, the memory database approach,
you can predict those with missing values,
right?
So you can imagine,
you have iterative approach where you
first do some preliminary prediction and
then you can use the predictor values to
further improve the similarity function.
Right so this is here is
a way to solve the problem.
And the strategy of this in the effect
of the performance of clarity filtering,
just like in the other heuristics,
we improve the similarity function.
Another idea which is actually very
similar to the idea of IDF that we
have seen in text research, is called
the inverse user frequency or IUF.
Now here the idea is to look at the where
the two users share similar ratings.
If the item is a popular item that has
been aah, viewed by many people and
seemingly leads to people interested
in this item may not be so interesting.
But if it's a rare item and
has not been viewed by many users.
But, these two users
[INAUDIBLE] to this item.
And they give similar ratings, and it
says more about their similarity, right?
So it's kind of to emphasize
more on similarity
on items that are not
viewed by many users.
[MUSIC]